<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The searchers for schism search'd, or, Their pretended questions for conscience sake answered wherein is proved that those baptized congregations under laying on of hands are not guilty of schism in separating from them : shewing, in opposition to their threeforld  hypothesis, that their church constitution is not true, separation from them proved lawful, the truth and authority of the doctrine about which they separate, vindicated / humbly presented to all concerned [by] J. Griffith ...</title>
            <author>Griffith, John, 1622?-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 180 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42146</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G2003</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41670</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">31355748</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 31355748</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110647</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42146)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110647)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1739:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The searchers for schism search'd, or, Their pretended questions for conscience sake answered wherein is proved that those baptized congregations under laying on of hands are not guilty of schism in separating from them : shewing, in opposition to their threeforld  hypothesis, that their church constitution is not true, separation from them proved lawful, the truth and authority of the doctrine about which they separate, vindicated / humbly presented to all concerned [by] J. Griffith ...</title>
                  <author>Griffith, John, 1622?-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 115 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, tightly bound, and torn, with print show- through and loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baptists --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-03</date>
            <label>Robyn Anspach</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110647:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110647:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>SEARCHERS</hi> for <hi>SCHISM</hi> SEARCH'D: Or, Their pretended <hi>Queſtions for Conſcience ſake,</hi> ANSWERED.</p>
            <p>Wherein is proved, That thoſe Baptized Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations under <hi>Laying on of Hands,</hi> are not guilty of <hi>Schiſm</hi> in Separating from them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shewing, Suppoſition to their threefold</hi> Hypotheſis,
<list>
                  <item>1 That their Church Conſtitution is not true.</item>
                  <item>2 Separation from them proved lawful.</item>
                  <item>3 The Truth and Authority of the Doctrine about which they Separate, vindicated.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Humbly preſented to all concerned, J. Griffith,</hi> a cordial deſirer of the flouriſhing <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Church in Unity and Peace, with <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and Truth; but, <hi>Societas in <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> tantum ab<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt ab <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pl<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> n<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>aria con<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> pariter <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 18, 17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He that is firſt in his own cauſe ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth juſt, but his neighbour cometh and ſearcheth him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed for the Author 1669.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:110647:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110647:2"/>
            <head>To the Baptized Diſciples not under lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of Hands, is heartily wiſhed the true knowledge of God, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Love, with ſubmiſſion to the whole Doctrine of Chriſt, deſired in the way of Truth.</head>
            <p>WHen we firſt ſaw your Book, read the Title, and how you pretend your Queſtions are for Conſcience ſake; we thought Silence for ſome time would be the beſt Anſwer, conſidering what hath formerly past between us about the Difference ſtill depending, and the preſent face of things, as they now ſhew themſelves in the world.</p>
            <p>But when we came to take a view of your E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, finding it writ by ſome spirit inraged, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than one deſirous of ſatisfaction from any ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, ſober, conſcientious ſcruple, or doubt, We were invited the more to conſider your Queſtions; and finding them to ſtrike at the root, fill'd with ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſity, taunting and inſulting terms, rather than a ſpirit ſo much as sprinkled with conſcious, candid, and ſerious aims, though you give your ſelves the name, as the obſcure Parents of this (in ſome
<pb facs="tcp:110647:3"/> ſenſe) abortive Child of the Lovers of Truth and Peace, which bespeaks the Babe both conceived and brought forth under the melevolent Aspects of ſome froward contentious (and yet pretended glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Chriſtian) deſign.</p>
            <p>Your Epiſtle, which as the Midwife that brought the Child into the world, we find uſhers it in with caluminations ſo foul, and of ſuch a ſort, as if it were intended to ſcale <hi>Rome</hi>'s Walls, and bid De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance to the Man there that uſurps the Keyes of Heaven and Hell.</p>
            <p>And withal, that way may be made for its more laudable entrance and progreſs, ſhe no ſooner ſpeaks, but, like <hi>Athalia,</hi> ſhe cryes Treaſon, treaſon, (the Lord's Prerogative is invaded) when alas, ſhe was the Traytor her ſelf; and then ſhe marcheth on, and proclaims them (ſhe is ſent to with ſo much pretended calmneſs) to be like the Man at <hi>Rome,</hi> uſurpers of the Keyes of Hell and Death.</p>
            <p>But how much the mark is miſſed is evident e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, for who more free and ready to ſtop up the way to Hell, and open the way to Heaven, ſo far as lies in them, by all the abilities they have, and endeavours they can uſe, than they whom you brand with the aforeſaid Uſurpation. Though we would not make the road to Heaven as the fooliſh Woman and clamourous doth the way to her Houſe, ſaying, Stolen waters are ſweet, and bread eaten in ſecret is pleaſant, to her guests.</p>
            <p>And though your Babes-Uſher hath got the knack
<pb facs="tcp:110647:3"/> on't to clamour with ſo much ſcurrility, by ſuch oyly lines, perhaps borrowed from ſome other Pen, yet is it an argument of a weak Cauſe rather than other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, it being uſual, when there is no better wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons to make uſe of ſuch, with this gloſs, <hi>The Lords Prerogative is invaded,</hi> and <hi>what wilt thou do to thy great Name?</hi> and the like; when you your ſelves are the invaders of that Royal Prerogative of the Lord's Anointed, by not ſuffering his Princely Authority to be obeyed without controule from you; and ſuch his leige People to whom his Prerogative and Name is more dear than their lives, as ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent teſtimony hath been given, and further may through his grace, ſhould he call for it. You ſtudy against wayes of obtractation.</p>
            <p>But how eaſie a matter is it for men to pretend to Conſcience in their own Caſe, and with the ſame Pen, bespatter the Conſciences of others with foul inormities of meer pretences under that cloak, as if they made bates, and pretended Conſcience; but let the ſober inspect this new-born Babe, and they will ſee make-bate writ in the face of him, though it hath Conſcience for its Name, and is ſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named a Lover of Truth and Peace; and do but trace it in its proceedings, and let but its conception be calculated, and they will find it both conceived and brought forth to that end, it being furniſhed with Confidence ſufficient to paſs it without ſuspition of being tardy of any ſuch thing as make-bate, while it can talk of Peace and Unity among Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb facs="tcp:110647:4"/> and pretend to more than ordinary zeal to it; and that it may go abroad without jealouſie of the contrary, all that ſtands in its way, muſt be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred as maintainers of Notions, catch'd up and charged upon Conſcience, without regard had to the intereſt of Religion, yea, and renting and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning away from all that agree not with them, when there is nothing leſs intended by you, than to run diviſions among us that are united in that thing under debate.</p>
            <p>And for the more effectual accompliſhment of this deſign, we muſt alſo be rendred as ſuch that take upon them to judge all that come not up to the ſame dimenſions with us, not to have God, nor to have communion with God, when our judgment in that caſe is, Thoſe that tranſgreſs and abide not in the Doctrine of Chriſt, have not God as his Church hath; not that thereby you or any man is judged by us, to have, or not to have God: And as for you, we have before given our Teſtimony, that we can, and do love you for the Truths ſake you own, ſo far as you have gone, or ſo far as you do own the Truth; but we cannot, nay we dare not love you with the love of Brethren in the true and right order of the Gospel. See Gods Oracle, and Chriſts Doctrine, <hi>page 94.</hi> then have you no cauſe to render us, as judging all but our ſelves in no ſenſe to have God, nor communion with God.</p>
            <p>And if you have better Arguments to prove your in ereſt in Chriſt than laying on of Hands, we
<pb facs="tcp:110647:4"/> have no cauſe to grieve at it, but to rejoyce; and can with all our hearts wiſh you have; for laying on of Hands can be none for you, (and it will be well if it be none againſt you) who have ſo long oppoſed it with ſo much bitterneſs, as you have done, and and ſtill do. But be we eſteemed your Friends or your Enemies, for ſaying, you are not a Church rightly Conſtituted, and ſo have not God as his Church; we muſt ſtill ſay it, until our Judgments and Conſciences be otherwiſe perſwaded by his Word; and if you will not believe what we ſay, we muſt leave it to the revelation of the righteous Judgment of the Lord, who will then make the deciſion of that, and alſo of your uncharitable judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of us, That if we could execute all (as you ſay) we condemn, then who ſhall be ſaved? you had as well ſaid, none; though thanks be to God we have our teſtimony on high, how much we have laboured and travelled for the Salvation of Souls; nor have you any cauſe to ſay, The Devil may have a Writ of Eaſe from any Judgment or Practice of ours; for, to the praiſe of God we ſpeak it, we have been by him made Inſtruments to turn men from Darkneſs to Light, and from the power of Satan to God, and not a few: but if any do give the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil a Writ of Eaſe, and bring Prey to the Den of that great Devourer, it is more like to be you that ſeek to keep men from the Truth, and that leave no ſtone unturned, to draw them that are in it, to the
<pb facs="tcp:110647:5"/> like diſ-eſteem you your ſelves have of it: And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, before you had charged others with Church-dividing, you ſhould firſt prove your ſelves to be a true Conſtituted Church, and then cry out against the Ignorance and Pride of thoſe that Separated from you; but while that beam is in your eye, how can you diſcern aright the moat in anothers? for as the Devil can dance at diſcord, ſo he can dance at concord, in confuſion and diſorder; when Unity is kept in Iniquity and Error, nothing can pleaſe the Father of Lyes better, promote his intereſt, enlarge his kingdom, and give a more ſecure Writ of Eaſe than that will; and therefore, if he be no better furniſhed, than where Unity is kept with Truth, and Unity in Iniquity, and Error is avoided, he may go look for Men and Arms where he can find them; for where Unity and Truth are together, and Truth and Unity are individuals, he will find none: And what will lay the Church more open to ruine and ſpoyle, than Unity in Error and Sin? and who, that is a Chriſtian, can rejoyce in ſuch Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies? the Devil ſhall gain by ſuch victories, yet will Church-diviſions do much, and cauſe her Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to triumph; let them take it to themſelves that are guilty thereof: Men in ſuch caſes most times miſs the mark, and lay not the ſaddle on the right horſe, but ſatisfie and pleaſe themſelves by charging others with that they want proof of, that ſo the Plea for themſelves may the better
<pb facs="tcp:110647:5"/> paſs for Not guilty, by crying up lawful Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to be Church-Renting, and a wounding Chriſts Body. And who will ſooner reflect the want of Knowledge, and Pride, than ſuch who are proud, knowing nothing, but doting about Queſtions? <hi>1 Tim 6.3, 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And how many men might ſilently go to their Graves without noiſe, had they not ſecured their Names, and in ſome kind their Reputation, by ſuch doting ways, and contendings againſt Truth, by branding others with the infamous character of Church-breaking? And while they do this, kindle a Fire to themſelves, and then delight in the ſparks thereof; withal reflecting the guilt of it on others, being ambitious that none are ſo holy, humble, and wiſe as they: and beſides, think it their duty to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice in the flame of their own fire, all their abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and parts, to promote their intended deſigns; not ſtanding much upon it, if to help forward the Work they venture to adde a little Hypocriſie, that with fair words and feigned ſpeeches, they might the better deceive the hearts of the ſimple: And that by ſtigmatizing others with the name of fooliſh Builders, and unskilful Phyſitians, you (like <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom)</hi> might get in place your ſelves; and while you pity the ſtate of others in this defect, crave the work your ſelves, as Builders, and the Cure, as Phyſitians; who yet have not attained the skill to lay a foundation. And if your skill to cure, be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o
<pb facs="tcp:110647:6"/> better than to build; there's but ſmall hopes for them that imploy you, but to be deſtroyed by your Building, and to die by your Practice.</p>
            <p>And moſt ſure it is, that this will be the iſſue, if ſuch unskilful Builders and Phyſicians be courted as they have been by ſome, to lend their aſſistance and advice; whoſe pride and intereſt is ſuch, that will not ſuffer them to be controul'd in their work, ſince their hearts are ſo ſtout, and their conceits of themſelves are ſo high, that they will not indure that ſhould be amended, which they have unskilfully built. What will then an agreement to joyn with you, to build, &amp; to cure (though ſtiled happy) prove, but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle better than deſtruction, and a languiſhing under an incurable diſeaſe, whoſe Reputation will not admit of any Regulation, that have ſo long made oppoſition against the true Rules of ſure and ſafe Building? And then how ſhall they become Truths Proſelytes, that have rejected it ſo long, without aſſuming the guilt of what they ſtand charged with, which may expoſe them to reject Conviction, rather than loſe their Credit and Reputation? For which they must ſay, we make cauſleſs Separation, hating them, and caſting them out, when none they charge are guilty of the one, nor of the other, as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to your Queſtions will inform you; which we preſent to your ſerious Conſideration; believing that Peace is the bleſſing of the moſt High, when Truth and Purity joyn hands with it. And O how happy
<pb facs="tcp:110647:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> a thing, and deſirable, is ſuch a Peace and Unity! And how much longed for! But ah! when will it once be? How can this ſo deſirable a thing be hoped for, while Truth and You ſtand at a diſtance? Your ſubjection to Chriſt, in owning and obeying that ſacred Appointment of his, which you have made ſuch oppoſition againſt, may heal the Breach, by which you will be baptized into one Body with us; and ſo you and we may grow up together a Temple and holy Habitation of God through the Spirit.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. G.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:110647:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110647:7"/>
            <head>The Searchers for Schiſm ſearched.</head>
            <p>MEeting with a ſmall Book called <hi>A Search for Schiſm,</hi> and finding with what ſpecious and glorious pretences it comes forth, and how reproachful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yea and falſly the Authors thereof do repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thoſe diſſenting from them; leſt they ſhould inſult yet more, and trample upon that ſacred Truth they contend againſt and oppoſe, We therefore thought it neceſſary that their Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhould be anſwered.</p>
            <div n="1" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 1.</head>
               <p>Whether a Congregation of people, that have confeſſed their ſins, and profeſſed their Faith in Chriſt for the pardon of them, and thereupon are baptized; reſolving by Gods aſſistance further to believe, do, and ſuffer what they ſhall from time to time underſtand to be according to the Will of God; We demand whether a people ſo qualified and congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated, ought not to be esteemed a Church of Chriſt, and Members in particular? <hi>1 Cor. 12.13.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>Before we come to anſwer, it will be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110647:8"/> that we obſerve ſome few things which lie hid in this Queſtion.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the difference depending between you and us, is about laying on of hands on bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized Believers, as ſuch.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That you at the preſent are ignorant, and do not underſtand laying on of hands to be your duty, according to the will of God, to ſubmit to.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That if you did underſtand (as aforeſaid) laying on of hands to be according to the will of God your duty, you would do it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And you being thus qualified, de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and whether you ought not to be eſteemed a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>urch of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>Theſe things premiſed, we now anſwer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. How can you be ignorant that laying on of hands is your duty to do, when one of you, and one that is eſteemed eminent among you for parts and knowledge, yea, and one of the chief, if not the alone Author of your <hi>Search,</hi> did not very long ſince receive laying on of hands upon the ſame ground, and to the ſame end we practiſe it; giving of it firſt under his own hand, as is ſtill to be ſeen.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Can he then be ignorant that laying on of hands is his duty to do, according to the will of God, when he ſhall ſubmit to it as to one of the firſt Rudiments of Chriſtianity? Either he did ſubmit with underſtanding, or he offered the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110647:8"/> Sacrifice of Fools, which know not what they do; or did he deſign to deceive the Brethren that adminiſtred Prayer and laying on of hands upon him, that ſo he might be the better able, (being now admitted a Member of a Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion under laying on of hands) and with the leſs ſuſpition, to undermine that part of the Foundation on which the Houſe was built? To ſay he did as Fools do, would be too ſaucy a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection; to ſay he received laying on of hands deſignedly, would proclaim that action of his rather Jeſuitical than Chriſtian, and conclude him notorious for Hypocriſie.</p>
               <p n="3">3. How can it be thought he ſhould not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand prayer and laying on of hands to be a foundation-Principle of the Doctrine of Chriſt, when he hath more than once in the preſence of many people confeſs'd it ſo to be, and at length confeſt it under his hand, &amp; ſubmited to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe thereof, as one of the firſt Rudiments (to uſe his own terms) of Chriſtianity?</p>
               <p n="4">4. But ſuppoſe he nor you underſtand not laying on of hands to be your duty according to the will of God, will it follow that therefore you ought to be eſteemed a Church of Chriſt rightly and duely conſtituted? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We believe that there are many that ſprinkle their Children (whoſe Confeſſion of Sin, and Profeſſion of <hi>Faith in Chriſt,</hi> we and you can own) that you have ſo much Charity for, that did they believe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110647:9"/> it to be the duty of Believers only to be bapti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>zed, and not Children, they would ſubmit to Baptiſm themſelves, and never ſprinkle, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> own ſprinkling of Babes more: Will this give you ſufficient ground to eſteem them a Church of Chriſt? You will ſay, No: And why no<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Becauſe they are not baptized according to the will of God, and Baptiſm is one Principle o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Doctrine of Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. Even ſo ſay we, having ſo much Charity for ſome of you that did you underſtand laying on of hands to be your duty to ſubmit to, according to the will of God, you would do it: yet may you not be eſteemed a right conſtituted Church, though you have obeyed one Principle of the Doctrine of <hi>Chriſt</hi> more than they which ſprinkle their Babes, and are right in Faith and Repentance becauſe you are not under laying on of hands which alſo is one Principle of Chriſts Doctrine, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2. Ignorance will be no excuſe, where Knowledge may be had; we may not own you a true conſtituted Church for your Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If you be ignorant that laying on of hand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is your duty to ſubmit to, where is the fault? Not in God, <hi>He giveth liberally, and upbraidet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not, Jam.</hi> 1.5. nor in his VVord, <hi>that is able t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> make a man wiſe to Salvation, through faith i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. Is it not written i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Scriptures of Truth, and hath it not bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:110647:9"/> aſſerted both by preaching and printing, as you your ſelves know and ſay. Inſomuch that the Light of this Truth (had you not rejected it) might have ſhined into your hearts, long ere this day, and you brought to the knowledge of the mind of Chriſt. If they have not enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened you, who knows? ſince no anſwer hath been given by you to thoſe Books wherein Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of Hands hath been aſſerted; eſpecially <note n="*" place="margin">See Gods Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, and Christs Doctrine, <hi>p. 91.</hi>
                  </note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that you have been invited to anſwer them, with a promiſe, that the miſtake and error ſhould be acknowledged, when you ſhould prove laying on of hands to be no Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Chriſts Doctrine.</p>
               <p n="6">6. You do not onely ſeem to plead igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but you give us to underſtand that you are reſolved to believe, do, and ſuffer what from time to time ſhall be made known unto you, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> further than your preſent attainments. The words are good words, it's true; but how can they agree with your practice? For from before the time we departed from you, down to this day, you have been conſtant and unwearied op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers of laying on of hands, ſpeaking evil of the way, diſputing publickly againſt it, and now laſtly make oppoſition in your <hi>Queſtions for Conſcience-ſake,</hi> as you pretend, with ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous and taunting expreſſions, as in ſeveral
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110647:10"/> places doth appear, which makes it not eaſie to be believed, that if you are ignorant you deſire to underſtand, or underſtanding, reſolve to do as you ſay you will.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Will reſolving to do the Will of God when known in a fundamental, give you the eſteem of a Church of Chriſt rightly Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? if you, then it will give others we hope in your eyes the like eſteem that are ſhort of you in one principle of Chriſts Doctrine, as you are of us in another; and if ſo, then ought you to eſteem thoſe in the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependant</hi> way, eſpecially thoſe of them that believe Chriſt died for all, as you do, between whom there is no fundamental difference but in Baptiſm of Water, and that only too about the ſubject and manner of Baptizing; and no doubt but they are as ready to atteſt their reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to own and ſubmit to Baptiſm as Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, or any other thing whatſoever, ſhall from time to time be made known to them, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the will of God, as you are, or can be.</p>
               <p n="8">8. And whereas you ſay you are not only reſolved to believe, and do, but alſo to ſuffer, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Your actions, ſome of you, and thoſe ſome, none of the meaneſt for place and parts, will rather ſpeak the contrary; witneſs their freeing of themſelves from the yoke of Suffering by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110647:10"/> ſinful ſwearing, out-living their Teſtimony for Chriſt, preferring the world and their intereſt therein above his righteous Cauſe.</p>
               <p n="9">9. We then have cauſe to doubt, whether you are ignorant as you inſinuate, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved as you ſay; but if you are, we thus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer your demand, That it is not any Peoples reſolving to believe, do, and ſuffer, what here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſhall be made known to them, &amp;c. but the knowing and doing what is according to the Will of God, that will make them a right con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Church, and Members in particular, though you are, or may be eſteemed baptized Diſciples.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 2.</head>
               <p>Whether any other qualifications, &amp;c. <hi>viz.</hi> then is ſet down in the firſt Queſtion, are required of God, as pre-requiſits to Church Communion, and Church Memberſhip; if ſo, ſhew us what thoſe things are, and where they are ſo required?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. If we ſhould grant, as we do not, that God requires no other qualification than what you mention, as pre-requiſits to Church Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; yet have you not found the Schiſm, but muſt ſearch nearer home for it, if you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to find it; becauſe you are not the men ſo qualified as you intimate you be, as may well be perceived without ſecret ſearch by any, let but thoſe qualifications you ſpeak of, be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110647:11"/> with the actions of thoſe, time after time, that are of higheſt eſteem amongſt you.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But if you were qualified, as you ſay you are, yet will not that prove you a Church whoſe Conſtitution is right; for God requires laying on of hands, which is one Principle of the Doctrine of Chriſt, and one of the firſt ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments of Chriſtianity, as you have confeſſed, as pre-requiſits to Church Communion; But then you demand, where God requires it as a pre-requiſit to Church Communion: We then demand of you, where God requires Water Baptiſm as a pre-requiſite to Church Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion? If you ſhall ſay that Baptiſm is one Principle of Chriſts Doctrine; ſo is laying on of Hands, as well as Baptiſm, numbred among the principles of Chriſts Doctrine, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2. But if you ſhall ſay, that there is more in the Scripture to be ſaid for Water Baptiſm, than there is for laying on of Hands; we ſay, if there be more ſaid for Baptiſm in the Scripture than is for laying on of Hands, all that is ſaid cannot make it more than a foundation prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, and ſo is laying on of hands.</p>
               <p n="3">3. What if there be more ſaid in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for Faith towards God, than is for Baptiſm of Water, as there is in many things agreeing to it, yet is it no more than a foundation prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Chriſts Doctrine, and ſo is the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Baptiſm, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. And will it then
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110647:11"/> follow, becauſe there is more ſaid in Scripture for Faith towards God, than is ſaid for the Baptiſm of Water, that therefore Baptiſm is not required of God as a pre-requiſite to Church Communion; even ſo, ſhould it be granted, that there is more ſaid for Baptiſm, in ſome one thing, or more, than is for laying on of Hands, it doth not follow but that laying on of Hands being numbred by the Apoſtle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the foundation principles of Chriſts Doctrine, as well as Baptiſm, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of God as a pre-requiſite to Church Communion, and Memberſhip, as well as Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Again, where is the belief of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Dead required of God as pre-requiſite to Church Communion? yet is that a principle of Chriſts Doctrine <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. and ſuch a one, that if not owned and believed, you would not own ſuch a People ſhould be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Church Communion and Church Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip. If you ſhould ſay, that to deny the Reſurrection is an Errour which makes Faith vain, and concludes us yet in our ſins; we ſay that it is no more than a Principle of Chriſts Doctrine, and ſo is laying on of Hands, and yet you cannot ſhew where its required of God, <hi>viz.</hi> The belief of the Reſurrection of the Dead, as a pre-requiſite to Church Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; it doth not therefore follow but that if
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110647:11"/> you are ſo qualified as you ſay you are, ſhould you deny or not believe the Reſurrection of the Body, that you are a Church Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable, or Church Members; therefore there is other qualifications than thoſe you ſpeak of pre-requiſite to Church Memberſhip and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 3.</head>
               <p>If it ſhall be ſaid, that Churches ought to be found in the knowledge and practice of all Chriſts Doctrines: We demand, whether the knowledge and practice of all truths be indiſpenſably neceſſary to the conſtituting of Churches and Church Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We ſay that Churches ought to be found in the knowledge of all Chriſts Doctrine, (not Doctrines) and ſo we think will you ſay.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We do not ſay never the more for that, that the knowledge and practice of all truths is indiſpenſably neceſſary to the conſtituting of Churches and Church Members; for there are many truths, Churches rightly conſtituted, may be ignorant of; but the firſt Principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt, none ought to be ignorant of, or without the knowledge and practice, and be true conſtituted Churches and Church Members.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="question">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:110647:12"/>
               <head>Queſt. 4.</head>
               <p>If you ſay the knowledge and practice of all truths is not indiſpenſably neceſſary to the conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuting of Churches and Church Members; then we demand, that you would define what truths the knowledge and practice whereof is ſo indiſpenſably neceſſary as aforeſaid? and what truths and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices the ignorance of, may be conſiſtant with a true Church and Church Memberſhip?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. What truths the knowledge and practice of are indiſpenſably neceſſary to the conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Churches and Church Members, we have given you the definition of in our Anſwer to your <hi>3d Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Thoſe truths of higheſt moment, the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of, may be conſiſtent with a true Church and Church Members, are ſuch as belong to the perfecting and compleating the Church and Church Members in Chriſt, which a true Church may be ignorant of in her minority; as the Hebrew Church was about many things <hi>Paul</hi> had to ſay, hard to be uttered, becauſe they were dull of hearing, and were ſtill as Babes, who are unskilful in the Word of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.11, 12, 13.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thoſe truths of leſs moment, conſiſtent with a true Church, are waſhing of Feet, ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with a holy Kiſs, taking an Oath to end
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110647:13"/> ſtrife, the matters of Apparel, and ſuch-like; and who pray makes theſe things the Eſſentials of Communion, though you falſly ſay they are ſo made; no Congregation in <hi>England</hi> as we know of.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Yet may the matter of Apparel give juſt cauſe of reproof when Church Members ſhall exceed the bounds of moderation, and ſobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in their Apparel, to the grieving, wounding and offence of their fellow Brethren, and may amount to a ſin againſt Chriſt, when they ſhall ſtop their ear, and ſtiffen their necks againſt them that are ſo grieved and offended.</p>
               <p n="5">5. There may be many things done by Churches and Church Members, that are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, which may juſtly deſerve reproof; and if not repented of, may merit the cenſure of the Church. The Angel of the Church of <hi>Perga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos</hi> was reproved for ſin, for having thoſe in the Church that held the Doctrine of <hi>Balaam,</hi> to eat meat ſacrificed to Idols, and to commit Fornication: which Fornication was mixt Marriages, as ſaith <hi>Joſephus,</hi> and we think his authority as good in this caſe, as you can think Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi>'s is in laying on of Hands.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Angel of the Church of <hi>Pergamos</hi> is by the Spirit commanded to repent of this evil, the command backed with a commination, which proves that ſuch muſt be put out of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110647:13"/> Church that ſo hold, much more ſuch which ſo do.</p>
               <p n="7">7. But laying on of Hands we do indeed make Eſſential to Church Communion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a Principle of the Doctrine of Chriſt, as hath been proved now, and hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and never was diſproved by you, except asking queſtions be refutation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 5.</head>
               <p>We demand, whether there was not a Church of Chriſt in the world before his Aſcention? and whether any other qualification was <hi>then</hi> pre-requiſite to Church Memberſhip, than Confeſſion of Sins, and Faith in Christ for the remiſſion of them together with a being Baptized into his Name, and walking in a holy life and converſation? if you ſay any thing elſe was <hi>then</hi> required and practiſed, as Eſſential to Church Memberſhip, ſhew us what that was, and where it was ſo required and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed: And if you ſay nothing elſe was <hi>then</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired and practiſed, we demand, whether the Church of Chriſt was wanting of any thing <hi>then</hi> that was Eſſential to its being, whatever it might want as to its well-being? If you ſay it wanted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <hi>then</hi> that was Eſſential to its being, then we further demand how this People ſo continuing in Faith, Baptiſm and Holineſs of life, could ceaſe to be a Church of Christ after his Aſcention, though they might not come up to ſome of thoſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110647:14"/> others Truths, that were afterward revealed when the Spirit was made manifeſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We do not find that Chriſt before his Aſcenſion doth give the Name or Title of a Church to any, but onely calls his Followers Diſciples, as we might enumerate a multitude of places in the Evangeliſts.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We find that our Lord Jeſus, when <hi>Peter</hi> confeſſed that <hi>he was the Chriſt the Son of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God,</hi> anſwered <hi>Peter,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>Upon this Rock will I build my Church:</hi> He doth not ſay, <hi>I have built my Church upon this Rock,</hi> but, <hi>I will, &amp;c.</hi> ſpeaking in the future tenſe, Hereafter when I do build it; not that he had then built his Church, but was about the work, making all things ready as materials both for the Foundation and Building.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Nor is what we ſay deſtitute of good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; for his Diſciples might then confeſs and believe him to be the Chriſt, but could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him dead, riſen, aſcended, and that the Comforter was come, upon which, as upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rock or ſure Foundation, Chriſt would build hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Church, and hath, ſince his laſt Will and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament is in force by his Death, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.16, 17 for his Church now is founded upon theſe Baſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt is come, and died for our Sins, according to the Scriptures; believing that we in dut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ought to be baptiſed in his Name for the Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110647:14"/> of them, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38. &amp; 22.16. and pray, with laying on of hands, for the gift of the Spirit, which now is come ſince Chriſt is aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Father, according to his promiſe, <hi>John</hi> 16.7. to guide us into all Truth, and to be with us for ever, <hi>John</hi> 14.16, 17. as his alone Vicar on Earth, <hi>John</hi> 16.13, 14, 15. by which Spirit we are baptiſed into one body, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. believing that as he is riſen from the dead, he will alſo raiſe us up at the laſt day, <hi>John</hi> 6.40. and will come the ſecond time ſitting upon the Throne of his Glory to Judgement, and to render to every man as his work ſhall be. On all which, as on a Rock or Foundation, the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples could not be built in the time of Chriſts life, not till after his Aſcenſion, becauſe they were not then laid, nor could not till Chriſt was dead, riſen and aſcended to the Father: Yet in the time of his Life, as his Diſciples he was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent to inſtruct, teach, and inform them of all theſe things, as ſuch which ſhould be done and accompliſhed in their due and appointed time, <hi>viz.</hi> after he had ſuffered, was riſen and aſcended to the Father.</p>
               <p>But it may be objected, That Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. <hi>If he ſhall neglect to hear them, tell it to the Church;</hi> there Chriſt calls them a Church.</p>
               <p>That doth not follow, thoſe being words of direction and inſtruction which Chriſt gives
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110647:15"/> them, by which they might be guided when they had received power from on high to pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceed as a Church, to cenſure unholy and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly Walkers; not that they, before they were endowed with that power from on high, were to act as a Church to cenſure the impenitent, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> did they, as we read.</p>
               <p>You may further object, That Chriſt did break Bread with them, and therefore they we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then a Church.</p>
               <p>It is true, Chriſt did before his Paſſion inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute the Supper, he brake the Bread, and gave it to his Diſciples; but it was onely with the Twelve, the reſt of the Diſciples being abſent then doth it not follow that the Diſciples we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the capacity of a Church, becauſe the Twelve are ſingled out from the reſt of the Diſciples which ſhews (excepting him that was loſt) tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they were taken apart from the other Diſciples as thoſe that were appointed by the Lord to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Witneſſes in a more eminent way and manne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> than the reſt, of all thoſe things he ſhould ſuffer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And thoſe whom Jeſus had choſen and give<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> commandment to, not onely by his own mouth but through the Holy Ghoſt alſo, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.2. wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they ſhould teach others to believe and obſerve <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. Breaking Bread then at this tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> might not be ſolemnized as Church-communion which ought to be when the whole Body comet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> together, to commemorate the Body and Blood
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110647:15"/> of Chriſt, the one as broken, the other ſhed, and to ſhew the Lords death till he come; but rather was inſtituted then by Chriſt at the feaſt of the Paſſover, to ſhew them what they ſhould after he was aſcended do, &amp; alſo to teach others what they ſhould do and obſerve, when they were endowed with power from on high, and thereby were en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ighted to all things relating to Church-Power, and the adminiſtration of all Church-Ordinances; which until they were ſo impowered, they were onely to wait at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Luk.</hi> 24.49. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.4. If otherwiſe, why ſhould the reſt of the Diſciples be excluded, and not called to this laſt Supper of the Lord? If they broke Bread as a Church, the reſt of the Diſciples had as much right to that Communion as the Twelve, or elſe the Twelve onely were the Church, and the other Diſciples no part of it: And if a Church, why muſt they wait for power at <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi> This we humbly and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly offer to conſideration. And as for the reſt of your Queries and Demands which you multiply in this Queſtion, they are either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved and anſwered, or require none fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But</hi> (ſay you further) <hi>if you ſhall ſay they want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſomething while Chriſt was among them, eſſential to Communion; then we demand whether this doth not reflect a want of care in Chriſt, who left them ſo, and indeed want of underſtanding in thoſe that ſay
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110647:16"/> ſo? For if Chriſt had a Church before his aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that wanted any thing eſſential to its being, then it was a Church, and no Church, at the ſame time, which is abſurd to imagine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let what is aboveſaid be duly and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately weighed, and there will be no reflection upon Chriſt, nor ignorance in thoſe that ſay they were onely Diſcipl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, and not impowered as a Church before Chriſts Aſcenſion. It can reflect no want of care in Chriſt, becauſe they could not be in any other capacity than his Scholars, before the Spirit was given them; no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> were they capable to receive more than what Chriſt did communicate to them, and leave with them, until the Spirit was manifeſted; <hi>I have many things to ſay, but ye cannot bear them now, John</hi> 16.12. Then its no reflection upon Chriſt for want of care, conſidering the time, and the Diſciples incapacity to bear them then.</p>
               <p>Nor do we ſay Chriſt had a Church before his Aſcenſion (if they were a Church) that wanted any thing eſſential to its being in that diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; therefore you may keep your abſurdity till you have more occaſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 6.</head>
               <p>We demand whether thoſe qualifications that give us a Right to Baptiſm, do not give us a Right to the Lords Table?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:110647:16"/>
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Thoſe qualifications that give you a right to Baptiſm, do not give you a right to the Lords Table.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For confeſſion of ſins, and profeſſion of Faith in Chriſt for the pardon of them, are qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications that gives <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ht to Baptiſm; but they do not give the perſon ſo confeſſing and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, a right to the Lords Table, except he be firſt baptiſed, by your Principles and Practice, if we be not deceived by you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 7.</head>
               <p>We demand whether it be not ſinful to make more conditions of Communion, than ever God made? And whether the impoſing of any thing (though true) as the conditions of Church-memberſhip and Communion, which God hath not made a Condition, be not to keep thoſe out of the Church, that Chriſt would have in?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We grant it is ſinful to make more Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of Communion than ever God made.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And to impoſe any thing, though true, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Condition of Church-Memberſhip and Communion, which God hath not made a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ition, is to keep thoſe out of the Church that Chriſt would have in.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 8.</head>
               <p>If Chriſt hath required no other conditions of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110647:17"/> Church-Communion, than Confeſſion of Sin, Faith, Baptiſm, and a holy Life, whether you can by an Rule deny Communion to any that are ſo qualified. If ſo, ſhew that Rule.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Though it be true, that Confeſſion of ſin, Faith, Baptiſm, and an holy Life, be condition<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Communion, yet are there more condition<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> required by Chriſt, of Church-Communion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that thoſe: for the twelve Diſciples <hi>Paul</hi> foun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> had confeſſed their ſin, profeſſed their faith, and were baptiſed, yea, and wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> men of holy Lives, and yet they wanted ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conditions of Church-Communion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For theſe Diſciples were ignorant of the Doctrine of Baptiſms, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. knew no more than the Baptiſm of <hi>John;</hi> for they had not heard whether there were a holy Ghoſt, or no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 19.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They were not under laying on of hand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which God had appointed as the means h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> which the holy Ghoſt was given and received both which, <hi>viz.</hi> the Doctrine of Baptiſms an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> laying on of hands, are Principles of the Do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. And therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> truly conditions of Church-Communion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Water-Baptiſm, for it is by one Spirit we a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all baptiſed into one Body, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Then not to hear whether there were holy Ghoſt or no, as theſe Diſciples did not,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110647:17"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leſs defect in them, than for you to hear and read there is a holy Ghoſt promiſed to as many as obey Chriſt, and you not believe the Baptiſm thereof, but oppoſe and reject the means by which the Baptiſm of the Spirit is obtained, and by which we all are baptiſed into one Body, is a far greater defect, and want of the conditions Chriſt requires of Church-Communion in you, than was in them.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Then can we deny Communion with you, becauſe Chriſt requires more conditions of Church-Communion than you yet have; for which we have theſe Rules, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.6. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.4, 5. <hi>Cum multis aliis.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 9.</head>
               <p>Whether the Baptiſed Congregations that are not under laying on of hands, do not make thoſe quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications above mentioned, abſolutely neceſſary to Church-communion and Church-memberſhip? And if ſo, why ſhould you refuſe Communion with them?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. You may well make a queſtion of it, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you do make thoſe qualifications you men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before, abſolutely neceſſary to Church-communion and Church-memberſhip, when in your ſixth Queſtion you demand, <hi>Whether thoſe qualifications that give you a Right to Baptiſm, do not give you a Right to the Lords Table?</hi> Which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mporteth, That thoſe which have a Right to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110647:18"/> Baptiſm, by virtue of ſome qualifications, have a right to the Lords Table by virtue of the ſame qualifications at the ſame time; and if they that have a right to Baptiſm, have at the ſame time a right to the Lords Table, they may by right have Church-communion though they be not baptized.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Therefore we muſt Anſwer you, That we cannot tell, or we do not know, whether you do make thoſe qualifications you mention, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary to Church-communion, and Church-memberſhip, becauſe in your ſixth Queſtion, you more than ſeem to leave out Baptiſm as a qualification, which you put in elſewhere as one.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But if you do make all thoſe qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons you mention, abſolute neceſſary to Church-communion and Church-memberſhip, you have been already told why we refuſed Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with you; it will be too much in this place to ſay it again.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 10.</head>
               <p>Whether you have not at ſome turns, both by practice and profeſſed agreements, owned thoſe for Churches and Church Members, that are bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tized Believers as aforeſaid? and if ſo, by what rule can you refuſe to have Communion with them?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. It is not without cauſe to believe, that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:110647:18"/> is too true, that ſome have been daubing with untempered morter, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.10, 11, 12, 13, 14. to heal the hurt ſlightly, ſaying, Peace peace, when there was no peace, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.14, having both by practice and profeſſed agreements, owned you for Churches rightly conſtituted.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It were well if thoſe that have ſo practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and agreed, would remember from whence they are fallen, and repent, and do their firſt works before it be too late, and their Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick be removed out of its place, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.5.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And they their giving ſo much advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to you, who oppoſe ſome part of the mind of Chriſt which they believe and practiſe, which is now taken up by you, and uſed as weapons againſt the truth they practiſe, doth cry aloud upon them to repent, and ſmite upon the thigh, ſaying, <hi>What have we done?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. For if ſuch practice and profeſſed agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be according to the will of God, wherein they have owned you Churches, and Church Members rightly conſtituted, Communion by no rule can be refuſed, but ought to be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and held with you.</p>
               <p n="5">5. But we ſay, whatever ſome have practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and profeſſedly agreed, that you are not Churches, nor Church Members rightly conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, becauſe you have not yet laid all the principles of the foundation, but are wanting in ſome one, if not more, of the firſt rudiments
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110647:19"/> of Chriſtianity, as you have confeſſed laying on of Hands to be; We therefore refuſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with you by the above-mentioned rules in our Anſwer to your <hi>8th Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 11.</head>
               <p>But if you ſhall deny you have ſo owned them, then we demand whether you that are under laying on of Hands, do not daily receive ſuch into your Communion that have been converted and bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by thoſe not under laying on of Hands, without taking an account of their Faith, or baptizing them again? If it ſhall be anſwered, you do ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them; becauſe they had confeſſed their Faith, and were baptized before: then we demand whether ſuch as you ſo receive were converted by, or made their confeſſion to, and received their bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm from, the Church or the World? If you ſay they were the Church; how dare you ſeparate from them you own to be Gods Church, though leſs perfect? If you ſay they were the World, they made their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion to, and did receive their baptiſm from, then ſhew us whenever God intruſted the world with, or otherwiſe how the world came by a power to take a Confeſſion of Faith, and to adminiſter a lawful Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm? If you ſhall ſay they that Baptized them you ſo receive, were neither the Church nor the World; then ſhew us a middle ſtate of men, that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with the lawful and due Adminiſtration of Gods Ordinances, that are neither the Church nor the World; if not, doth not this practice of yours
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:110647:19"/> declare you own thoſe for a Church of Chriſt, that are not under laying on of Hands? &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We confeſs that we which are under lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands, have received to laying on of hands, and then to Communion, ſome from you not under laying on of hands; nor did we take account of their Faith, nor baptize them again, becauſe we were ſatisfied in both, not inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring who converted them, thinking that not material, ſo they were converted.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To your next demand, we ſay, They were neither Baptized by the Church, nor the World, but by Diſciples; and therefore we dare to ſeparate from you, though not from them that God owns for his Church, though they ſhould be leſs perfect.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To your third demand, we ſay, Men and Women may be converted and baptized, and yet they that convert and baptize them, neither the Church, nor the World.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Philip (Asts</hi> 8.) converted and baptized the <hi>Samaritans</hi> and the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> but <hi>Philip</hi> was neither the Church nor the World; But you will ſay, <hi>Philip</hi> was a Member and a Deacon of the true Church; 'tis true, he was: but then <hi>Apollos,</hi> who taught diligently the things of the Lord at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and elſewhere (and its beyond a ſuppoſition to ſay, the twelve Diſciples, <hi>Acts</hi> 19. were baptized by him; but if not by
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:110647:20"/> him, by ſome other, whoſe attainments were no more than his) and he, if he did not bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize them, might as lawfully, as teach the things of the Lord, and by as good authority might Baptize them as they that did, if he did not; and he was neither the Church, nor a Member rightly Conſtituted; for he at that time knew only the Baptiſm o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>John, Acts</hi> 18.25.</p>
               <p n="5">5. So the Men and Women <hi>Philip</hi> Baptized at <hi>Samaria,</hi> were not a Church complete in their conſtitution, though they had confeſſed their ſins, believed and were baptized, but were thereby made materials fit, and framed ready to be put into the Building, which the Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were ſent by the reſt of the Apoſtles from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to do, who prayed and laid their hands on them, and they received the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.14. then were <hi>they all Baptized by one Spirit into one Body,</hi> according to 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. before which they were not a Church, nor Church-members according to right and true Church-conſtitution; nor were they the World, becauſe they were Believers baptized. So in like manner, the twelve Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples <hi>Paul</hi> found it <hi>Epheſus, Acts</hi> 19. were not a Church, becauſe they were not baptized by that one Spirit into one Body, nor were they and <hi>Apollo</hi>'s the World; becauſe they were Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers baptized, they are ſaid to be Diſciples, <hi>Acts</hi> 19.1.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:110647:20"/>6. Then is there a middle-ſtate of men, that were neither the Church, nor the World, that were entruſted with the lawful &amp; due Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of ſome of God's Ordinances, as <hi>Apollos,</hi> who taught and baptized; or if he did not baptize, yet ſome other did, no more authorized than he; and if one might lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, an hundred might by the ſame rule that were in no other capacity than he.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Then doth not our practice in receiving ſome that you have converted and baptized, as afore, declare we own you for Churches that are not under laying on of hands.</p>
               <p n="8">8. And whereas you again demand, <hi>Whether it was not agreed on at a general Meeting of El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, That ſuch as believe and are baptized, were in the account of the Scripture to be eſtimated a Church:</hi> We ſay, we know of no general Meeting of Elders where any ſuch thing was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver agreed, though we are apt enough to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that at a meeting of ſome Elders there have been ſuch non-ſcriptural agreements made.</p>
               <p n="9">9. But ſuch agreements you ſpeak of, make work for Repentance, let them be made by whom they will; and well may it be ſaid of thoſe Elders that make ſuch agreements, as was once ſaid of the Hebrew Church, they <hi>have need that one teach them again which be the firſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Oracles of God.</hi> Heb. 5.12.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:110647:21"/>10. And to your demand, <hi>Whether it hath not been permitted by, and practiſed among us, that thoſe which are under laying on of Hands, may and do lawfully marry with thoſe that are not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der laying on of Hands?</hi> We ſay, it hath been ſo permitted and practiſed; and ſince from thence you demand, <hi>Whether this was not, and is not eſteemed by us a marrying in the Church, and in the Lord?</hi> We ſay, that it is not a marrying in the Church, though we ſay it may be a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying in the Lord; ſince Believers baptized may be out of the World, and in the Lord, though not a right and true Church-ſtate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted according to the pattern Chriſt appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: The <hi>Samaritans</hi> that believed and were baptized, and <hi>Apollos,</hi> and thoſe twelve Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples mentioned afore, were in the Lord, yet not a Church, as hath been ſhewed. Thus you ſee we do not own you a Church in the Lord, therefore you may ſpare your laſt demand, <hi>(Whether it be not prodigiouſly abſurd to own you a Church in the Lord</hi>) till we do own you a Church in the Lord, and yet deny you a Church in the Lord. And whereas you ſay, <hi>you have Members fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to make us husband &amp; wives:</hi> Truly, not ſo fit neither, as we could and do deſire our Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers would make choice of; however not ſo fit as to be Church-Members at the Lord's Table.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="question">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:110647:21"/>
               <head>Queſt. 12.</head>
               <p>If a People congregated upon profeſſion of Faith, Baptiſm, and a Holy life, be a Church of God, and God requireth no other conditions in order to the conſtituting of Churches and Church-members, as appears by the light of the former queſtions, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our own practice and confeſſion at ſome turns. Then we demand, whether he that firſt ſeparated, and thoſe with him, did not make a ſeparation from ſuch a Church? and whether ſuch a ſeparation from the Communion of, or diſowning Communion with ſuch a Church, be not to make Diviſions and Schiſm in the Body of Christ?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We have already ſhewed you, that ſuch a People, no otherwiſe qualified than you are, cannot be a Church rightly conſtituted; and that God doth require more conditions than you have in order to the right conſtituting of Churches, and Church-members.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Nor doth it appear by any light your queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons give, that you have a true Church ſtate; for had we no other light to walk by, in finding out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> right conſtituted Church, than your queſtions, we ſhould be in the dark, ſtumble, and fall, as many of late have done, the more it's to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amented.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Nor doth it appear that you are a Church rightly conſtituted, never the more for what
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:110647:22"/> ſome back-ſliders have practiſed, and confeſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at ſome turns.</p>
               <p n="4">4. You may well call them <hi>turns,</hi> for tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they are indeed; for had they not turned fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the truth, as they were taught, and as they h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> believed, and as the Truth is in Jeſus, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> had never ſo practiſed, and confeſſed, as y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſay they have.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Then he that firſt ſeparated from you; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thoſe with him, did not ſeparate from Church, whoſe Conſtitution is according to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> will of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="6">6. And then ſeparation from you, and di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>owning Communion with you, whoſe Churc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtate is not true, is not to make Diviſions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Schiſms in the body. For,</p>
               <p n="7">7. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> after he had laid han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on the twelve he found at <hi>Epheſus, went into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Synagogue, and ſpake boldly for the ſpace of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Months, disputing and perſwading the thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> concerning the Kingdom of God,</hi> Acts 19.8.</p>
               <p n="8">8. He that ſeparated from you, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with him (after they were under Laying o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Hands) continued diſputing and perſwadi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the things concerning the Kingdom of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for more than the ſpace of three months.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul, when divers were hard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and believed not, but ſpake evil of the way bef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the multitude, departed from them, and ſepara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the Diſciples,</hi> verſ. 9.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:110647:22"/>10. So he that ſeparated from you, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>vers of you were hardened and believed not, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſpake evil of that way before the multitude, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aying, Laying on of hands was an invention <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Devil; <hi>Such a one's hands were holy, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ould keep their heads warm;</hi> with ſuch-like as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at) departed from you, and ſeparated the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſciples.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 13.</head>
               <p>Whether or no to deny Communion, or not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ive ſuch ſo qualified into Communion (as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) doth not ſavour of pride, ſingularity, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableneſs? And whether this doth not ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thize with the ſpirit of <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> who did not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ly refuſe to receive the Brethren, but forbid thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat would? <hi>3 John 9.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. For thoſe under laying on of hands to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Communion, and not to receive ſuch into Communion no otherwiſe qualified than you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re, doth not ſavour of pride, ſingularity, nor uncharitableneſs, becauſe your Church-conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution is not right.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If ſo, it hath no ſympathy with the ſpirit of <hi>Diotrephes</hi> to refuſe communion with you, nor to forbid thoſe that would: But it may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ride, hardneſs of heart, and unbelief in you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the cauſe you ſtoop not to Chriſt, but do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill perſiſt in making oppoſition againſt a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of his Doctrine, as you have done, and now do.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="question">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:110647:23"/>
               <head>Queſt. 14.</head>
               <p>Whether all that maintain ſuch a Separ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> from any Congregations that do believe in G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and are baptiſed, and walk holily, as aforeſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not guilty of Schiſm, and the ſin of <hi>Diotrep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> aforementioned?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>This is much the ſame with the laſt queſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> therefore we ſhall ſay onely this, That nei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all, or any which maintain a Separation from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon the grounds we do, are guilty of Sch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or the ſin of <hi>Diotrephes;</hi> for we maintain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Separation from Churches, nor Church-Mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers rightly conſtituted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 15.</head>
               <p>Whether we who you have ſeparated from, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> denied Communion to, have not uſed all Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and candid ways of Accommodation, that can rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonably be thought on? Have we not profeſs'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you, That if we ſaw laying on of hands (in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you practiſe it) a Duty, we would ſubmit to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Have we not alſo declared, That we are willing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the better finding out the Truth, that you ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> come and preach it among us? Have we not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> promiſed that we would never preach or di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> againſt it, to avoid offending of you? Nay, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we not practiſed this, by ſuffering your Coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Elders freely to preach among us, who preache<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your practice, without any oppoſition from us? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> further, have not many deſired to come under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:110647:23"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on of hands, if you would not make it the bounds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conditions of Communion, and tie them from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ning us, or having Communion with us after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rds? Whether then to refuſe Communion with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> after ſuch large and loving Condeſcenſions as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe, be not Schiſm greatly aggravated?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We believe you have of late uſed ways of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccommodation, (as you call them) but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er Chriſtian and candid, we have cauſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pect: When one of you ſhall deſire hands <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ght be impoſed on him by the Elders, upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s confeſſion given under his own hand, <hi>viz. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eſe may therefore certifie that I do believe the Doctrine of laying on of hands, mentioned</hi> Heb. 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>be one of the first Rudiments of Chriſtianity;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d yet now he is one of the chief Oppoſers of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t laying on of hands which he prophanely (to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no more) ſubmitted to: Which how Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>an and candid he therein was, may eaſily be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>cerned by any.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What if you have profeſſed, that if you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> laying on of hands to be a duty, in the way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> practiſe it, you would ſubmit to it? Will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> make your Church-ſtate true? It is more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n probable that thoſe in the Presbyterian and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dependant way, are as ready candidly to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, That did they ſee Baptiſm as you and we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ctiſe it, and laying on of hands alſo, to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Duty, they would ſubmit to both; doth it
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:110647:24"/> follow that your ſeparation and ours from t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is Schiſm?</p>
               <p n="3">3. And what if you have declaired that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are willing for the better finding out of Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (as you pretend) that ſome under laying o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hands ſhould come and preach it among y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Will that heal your ſore, and give you a ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and due Church-conſtitution?</p>
               <p n="4">4. And if you have promiſed never to pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nor diſpute againſt it, and if you have pract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſo, by ſuffering ſome Countrey Elders freely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> preach it among you, without any oppoſit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> from you; will theſe things you call condeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions, make you a right conſtituted Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that wanted a right conſtitution before? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſides, theſe condeſcentions might be juſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſtian and candid as his was, that deſired <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> come under laying on of hands, confeſſing i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be one of the firſt Rudiments of Chriſtian mentioned afore.</p>
               <p n="5">5. For there is cauſe to ſuſpect that t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> condeſcentions of yours were (rather than C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian and candid) deſigns to raze out that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the foundation, <hi>viz.</hi> Laying on of han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that is, raze out the belief and practice of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> time, or divide them about it that are unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as appears by what ſome of you have ſaid at ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> certain times, <hi>viz. That in ſeven years tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhould not have that eſteem of laying on of han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> now we have:</hi> And another at another <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:110647:24"/> ſhould ſay, <hi>That the Churches would ſtand with <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>rs in their eyes for their acting.</hi> Theſe conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcentions then, we ſay, rather tended to the <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>tting laying on of hands, and the eſteem of <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> out of their hearts that have ſubmitted to it, <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t ſo the practice of it might periſh and die in <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e; or if not ſo in all, yet then to cauſe a <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eceſſity of dividing about it, as great Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders as you be to Peace and Unity, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you might hide your diſobedience to Chriſt, <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd ſo paſs for currant a right-conſtituted <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hurch.</p>
               <p n="6">6. What if ſome of you have deſired to come <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nder laying on of hands? If they will make <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nful conditions, and bring them to us with <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eir deſire, we then have juſt cauſe to keep <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>em from ſo ſacred an Ordinance as laying on <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f hands is, until they ſhall come to the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence thereof, upon <hi>Chriſts</hi> terms and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, denying themſelves and their own.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Our refuſing then communion with you, <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ough whether in reality or pretence you have <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ade ſuch large and loving condeſcentions, (as <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou call them) ſince you ſtill want that loving condeſcention to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in obeying the Voice <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f that great Prophet, doth not make us guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of Schiſm; much leſs Schiſm greatly ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="question">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:110647:25"/>
               <head>Queſt. 16.</head>
               <p>Whether there are not many among you that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all they can to obstruct our reconciliation, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dermine all our Endeavours after Unity; cry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> down and condemning all but themſelves, leſt t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould moſt of all condemn themſelves, for mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unneceſſary diviſions in the Church of God? L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Painter in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> that had unskilfully pain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted a Cock, afterwards chaſed away all Cocks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Hens, lest the imperfection of his Art ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſcovered. And whether ſome among you in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> manner, having made this unskilful Separation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſay no worſe, have not caſt away all thoughts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> tenders of accommodation, and them that tender <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> leſt their foul deformity of Church-breaking ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> be detected?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We Will and can (without being aſham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thereof) freely acknowledge, That there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> many we hope among us, that do the beſt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> all they can to obſtruct ſuch a Reconciliatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as you would have, and to undermine (as yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> call it, though we have and will play abov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> board, and deal plainly) all your endeavo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for Unity, upon your terms of Unity: Whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> would rather tend to a going back, than a go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing on to perfection; and would be rather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> combination againſt the God of Order an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Truth, than a right well-approved Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion and Unity which he will ſay Amen to.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:110647:25"/>2. And in ſo doing we cry up truth, and not our our ſelves otherwiſe then ſervants to it, and lovers of it, knowing withal we are but unprofitable ſervants, for when we have done all, we have done no more than what is our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to do; nor do we cry down you, nor any, but as the Word of the Lord doth, for your diſobedience to Chriſt; we muſt not ſay, light is darkneſs, and darkneſs is light; wo be to us if we ſhould.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Neither do we obſtruct your endeavours after Reconciliation and Unity, from any ſelf-condemnation, of making Diviſions in the Church, knowing the guilt of Church-dividing, is not upon us; the Word of the Lord, and our own Conſciences not condemning us (but juſtifying us) though you unjuſtly do, that you might cover your ſelves under the mantle of mens approbation; which covering would be too narrow, had you by your late endeavours obtained your end, for your only way will be to lay your Church-Foundation right, ſubmit to that you have long quarrelled about, have reſpect to all the commands of the Lord Jeſus, ſo will you approve your ſelves to God, and be united to his People.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And as for your levity and flaſh about the Painter and his Cock; we never drove you away, as being aſhamed of any thing we have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one in ſeparating from you, but were alwayes
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:110647:26"/> willing to meet the beſt of you in any place, in publick Conference, or otherwiſe, by all wayes and means we lawfully might uſe, that our practice may be ſeen and tryed by the Word; and never upon that account chaſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way your Cock, nor no other, but have given yours battel again and again; nor do we fear to let ours be ſeen, being drawn not by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilful Painter in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> but by the Lord Jeſus in the <hi>Gospel;</hi> and therefore if we chaſe you away from us in point of Communion, it is leſt the deformity of your Fabrick, having but a piece or part Foundation, ſhould bring us in time to the ſame deformity, and diſorder with you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 17.</head>
               <p>Whether to break Communion with, or ſeparate from the Communion of a Church of Chriſt for ſome ſingle Errour not eſſential to a Church ſtate, be not a wounding to the weak, and a hardening to the wicked? Whether it doth not keep many out of the Church that would come in, and give occaſion of going out to many that are in? Whether Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions from a true Church, are not an in-let to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm and Infidelity? and whether all Chriſtians ought not to eſchew Diviſions, as great reproaches to Chriſtian Religion?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. A known Error is not to be ſuffered not tollerated in the Church of God; for by the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:110647:26"/> ſame rule, one may, more may, till the Church be fuller of ſtinking weeds, than choice flowers; and what will the weeds do, but eat out the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and thriving virtue of the flowers; we would not be ſo much the Devils friend, as to give him leave to plant, much leſs to ſuffer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of his planting to grow in the Lord's garden: Errour is of the Father of Lyes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Errour in the Church, though held but by ſome; if ſuffered; threatens the ruine of the whole body. <hi>Thou haſt them there, that hold the Doctrine of</hi> Balaam, <hi>&amp;c. Repent, or elſe I will come quickly, &amp;c.</hi> Errour ſuffered in ſome Members, may defile the body, and make it culpable of the ſin of Errour and Hereſie; <hi>A little Leaven leaveneth the whole lump.</hi> What will make the Church of God ſuch a ſinful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, unclean heap, as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is, ſooner than ſuch a tolleration.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Yet ſuch Errours, as not eating meats, though <hi>every creature of God be good, if it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with thanks-giving,</hi> and ſuch-like, being an Error not eſſential to Church-communion; to break Communion with a Church of Chriſt for ſome ſuch ſingle Error, may be a wounding to the weak, and a hardening to the wicked; and may keep many out of the Church that would come in, and give occaſion of going out to many th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y are in; and ſuch Diviſions from a true Church, may be an in-let to Atheiſm
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:110647:27"/> and Infidelity, and ought to be eſchewed by all Chriſtians, as great reproaches to Chriſtian Religion, and all this, Errors in Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> will do.</p>
               <p>The end of the <hi>Queſtions</hi> grounded upon the firſt <hi>Hypotheſis;</hi> the ſecond follows with their <hi>Anſwers.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 18.</head>
               <p>But if it ſhall be ſaid (as ſome of you have Preached and Printed) that laying on of Hands is eſſential to Church-communion, and that thoſe that are not under it, have not God, and are not in Communion with God; it is demanded, where are the Scriptures that either prove it eſſential to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and that thoſe that are not under it, have not Communion with God?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We have not only ſaid, but ſtill do ſay, that laying on of Hands is eſſential to Church-communion, and that thoſe who tranſgreſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſts Doctrine (of which Doctrine laying on of Hands is a Principle, as hath been confeſſed by you to be, in theſe words, <hi>viz. One of the firſt Rudiments of Chriſtianity)</hi> hath not Communion with God as his Church hath, eſpecially you, who have made ſuch wicked and abſurd oppoſition againſt it, as you have done. See our Anſwer to the <hi>12th Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Whereas you demand where the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are, that prove laying on of Hands to be
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:110647:27"/> eſſential to communion: we ſay they are in <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.19. But if you mean where are the Scriptures that <hi>in terminis</hi> will ſay ſo; we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, where are the Scriptures that in ſo many words will prove Baptiſm of Water, the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Dead, eternal Judgment, to be eſſential to Communion, every one of which you make an eſſential thereof, if you deceive us not; and if they, why not laying on of Hands, which is as truly as either of them a Foundation Principle of Chriſts Doctrine.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And ſince you demand where are the Scriptures that prove thoſe that are not under laying on of Hands, have not Communion with God; we tell you once again, that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures proving ſuch tranſgreſſors as you have been, who have both blaſphemed and propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that ſacred Appointment of the Lords, which is a Foundation Principle of his Doctrine, have not Communion with God as his Church, are in 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 9. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.24. <hi>Acts</hi> 3.22, 23. with many more in the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 19.</head>
               <p>If it ſhall be ſaid, as ſome of you have Printed and ſaid, That they that are not under laying on of Hands, have not God, becauſe they tranſgreſs, and not abide in the Doctrine of Chriſt, according to <hi>2 Joh. 9.</hi> We demand whether this be not vain Philoſophy; and whether by the ſame reaſon, we may not unchurch all the Churches that ever were
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:110647:28"/> in the world? Might it not be ſaid of the Church of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> that they had not God, becauſe they had not an acquaintance with, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently did not abide in all the Doctrine of Chriſt, relating to his Prieſtly Office; and whether thoſe many things that the Author had to ſay concerning Chriſts high Prieſthood, where the Doctrine of Christ, and Chriſts Oracles, or the Authors own inventions? if they were Chriſts Oracles or ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings which they could not receive becauſe they were dull of hearing, then they did tranſgreſs them; or why doth the Author find fault with them? And if they did tranſgreſs his ſayings and Oracles, and yet were a Church, and ſtill in communion, and are call'd Babes in Chriſt, how dare you ſay, they that abide not in all Chriſts ſayings, have not God? Did not the Churches in <hi>Aſia</hi> tranſgreſs? and might it not be ſaid of them that they did not abide in all Chriſts Doctrine, when <hi>Epheſus</hi> left her firſt love, when <hi>Pergamos</hi> retained thoſe in communion that held the Doctrine of <hi>Balaam,</hi> and the <hi>Nicholai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans;</hi> and the Church of <hi>Sardis</hi> kept their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with thoſe that had defiled their garments, and the <hi>Laodiceans</hi> are charged with Luke-warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and with being ſelf-conceited, and ſo are the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> in ſuffering the inceſtuous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; for which they ought by Chriſts Doctrine to have been humbled; we demand where the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures do declare theſe to be no Churches or incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable, though in many things they did tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:110647:28"/> the ſayings (and did not continue or abide in all the Doctrines and Oracles) of God? but if for all theſe they were ſtill owned as Churches, how then dare you ſay of them, or of any that ſhould fail like them, that they are no Churches, and have not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, becauſe they abide not in all his Doctrine?</p>
               <p>May not we rather turn the edge of that Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument upon your ſelves? thus:</p>
               <p>They that God owns for Churches, you ſin in diſowning; but God owns thoſe for Churches, that fail and come ſhort of many things, that Chriſt taught them; therefore you ſin in diſowning them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We ſay again, as ſome of us have Printed and ſaid, That you who have tranſgreſſed at ſuch a rate as you have done, and ſtill do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Doctrine of Chriſt, have not God as his Church, according to 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 9. nor is this vain Philoſophy (as you vainly enquire) but ſound words and wholſome Doctrine, which ſome of you will find to your ſorrow in the day of account, if you repent not.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Nor can any Church rightly conſtituted be unchurched by this reaſon, Becauſe Churches rightly conſtituted do not tranſgreſs againſt the Doctrine of Chriſt, but continue in it, and have both the Father and the Son; nor can it be ſaid of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Church, that they had not
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:110647:29"/> God, becauſe they underſtood not all thoſe things hard to be uttered, relating to the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Office of Chriſt; becauſe they had laid all the Principles of Chriſts Doctrine, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12. and 6.1, 2. which you have not, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in them, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.42. which you do not. Their fault for which the Apoſtle blames them, was, their ſlack and ſlow growth for the time they had been a Church, built upon the Rock Chriſt, and the Foundation-Principles of his Doctrine; by which neglect, they became dull of hearing, and were yet but as Babes unskilful in the Word of Righteouſneſs, and therefore he exhorts them to go on to perfection, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. that they might redeem their loſt time, and avoid the danger they ſtood in of falling away from what they were partakers of; their danger being ſuch, that if they ſhould ſtill continue ſlothful and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and not go on to perfection, they would at length fall from, and not continue in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt on which they were built, which if they did, there was no renewing them by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And indeed thoſe things of which they were ignorant, were thoſe parts of the Doctrine of Chriſt that belong'd to perfection, and their further growing up in him; but not the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation or beginning part of Chriſtians. Nor though they were dull of hearing, and could not receive thoſe things hard to be uttered, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:110647:29"/> to the Prieſtly Office of Chriſt; yet were they not Denyers, Oppoſers, and Diſputers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, as you have been againſt laying on of hands, more than twenty years.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Churches in <hi>Aſia</hi> were true conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Churches, and yet they tranſgreſſed and did not abide in all Chriſts Doctrine, for which cauſe (though the Spirit commends them in ſome things) they would not have God long as his Church, except they repented of thoſe Tranſgreſſions; <hi>I will remove thy Candleſtick out of its place, except thou repent,</hi> Rev. 2.5. By which it may plainly be perceived that their not abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the Doctrine of Chriſt, would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>church them that were true conſtituted Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, without Repentance, and doing their firſt works; though we will not ſay that they were <hi>ipſo facto</hi> declared no Churches of Chriſt, and ſuch as have no communion with God as his Church: Though we dare ſay that you, whoſe Church-conſtitution was never right, have not God as his Church; and we dare ſay, That the Churches in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> for ſuffering the inceſtuous perſon, and for ſaying, (ſome of them) <hi>the Reſurrection was paſt, &amp;c.</hi> after all lawful endeavours made, and means uſed to purge them from thoſe evils, had they not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented, but ſtill perſiſted in their Sin and Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitency, they would ſoon find they ſhould ceaſe to be a Church in God, and incommunicable
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:110647:30"/> for their not abiding in the Doctrine of Chriſt and Oracles of God. And thus much we dar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſay of them, or of any that fail like them, Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then (as afore) they are no Churches, have no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> communion with God as his Church, becauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they abide not in all his Doctrine.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Your Argument then is not of ſuch forc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to turn the edge of ours upon us, as you think <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for we anſwer it by diſtinction thus: If in you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> minor Propoſition, by failing and coming ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of many things Chriſt taught them, you mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fundamental things, we deny your minor. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> if you mean a failing and coming ſhort of man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> things Chriſt taught, as in the Churches of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> and the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> joyned with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitency, all lawful means being uſed to purg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them, we then likewiſe deny your minor. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> if you do not mean Fundamentals, nor ſins joyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed with Impenitency, as is aforeſaid; then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſay, God owns ſuch for Churches, and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould ſin if we did not; though they fail an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> come ſhort of perfection in many things. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then it follows not that God owns, or that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ought to own ſuch for Churches, that fail an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> come ſhort in Fundamentals, or the firſt Rud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments of Chriſtianity, as you do.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 20.</head>
               <p>Whether it be not an abuſe of that Text, <hi>2 Joh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to infer from the Doctrine of Chriſt there menti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed, That there can be no Churches nor Churc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:110647:30"/> Members, where every thing that Chriſt taught, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t obſerved and continued in: When by Doctrine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere, a man of a ſhort ſight may perceive is meant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e confeſſing that Jeſus Christ is come in the fleſh, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> appears verſ. <hi>7.</hi> which whoſoever abideth not in, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut ſhall deny, hath not God; and if this be not the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enſe, but the other <hi>(viz.)</hi> That he that continues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot in all Chriſts ſayings, hath not God, and is no Member of Chriſt; then either your ſelves are no Church, or elſe you are all perfect, and guilty of no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, becauſe all ſin is a tranſgreſſing Chriſts Doctrine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d he that ſaith he hath no ſin, is a Lyar, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ruth is not in him, <hi>1 John 1.10.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Who did you ever know infer from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 9. That there can be no Churches, nor Church-members, where every thing Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ught is not obſerved and continued in. 'Tis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rue, we ſay that every Principle of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>trine of Chriſt which he taught as the firſt Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iments of Chriſtianity, muſt be obſerved and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ontinued in, or elſe there can be no Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or Church-Members rightly conſtituted. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obſerved, believed, and practiſed, and not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ontinued in, they that now are a Church right <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n conſtitution, may (as afore is ſaid) ceaſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a Church for their tranſgreſſing, and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iding in the Doctrine of Chriſt, 2 <hi>John</hi> 9.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But you ſay, <hi>By Doctrine in that place, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eant (as a man of a ſhort ſight may perceive) the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:110647:31"/> confeſſing that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> appears, verſ.</hi> 7. Suppoſe this ſhould be t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> meaning, we demand whether every one th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> verbally ſo confeſſeth, and doth not verbally d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny Chriſt to be come in the Fleſh, doth anſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the mind of the Spirit in that Text, and ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> both the Father and the Son, ſo long as he ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth by ſuch a Confeſſion, we think you wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> not ſo ſay; for if you ſhould, then muſt yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> own <hi>Rome</hi> to be a Church of Chriſt: Becauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they ſtoutly confeſs with their mouths, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bide by it that Chriſt is come in the fleſh, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and will burn them that ſhall deny it; now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this be the meaning of the Text, then hath <hi>Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> both the Father and the Son, and doth not tranſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>greſs, but continue in the Doctrine of Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and thouſands more beſides, who will thus con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſs Chriſt to be come in the fleſh, but know yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not that in works they deny him? If then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> man ſhort-ſighted may ſee that by Doctrine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> meant a confeſſing of Chriſt to be come in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fleſh, that confeſſion muſt be more than verb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> as a man very ſhort-ſighted may perceive; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that by confeſſing Chriſt, is to own him to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Prince and a Saviour, to believe, obey, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> do what he hath taught, and to continue in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Doctrine. So then, though it may be as yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſay, yet is it not to be thought, that onely th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſingle and alone confeſſing of Chriſt to be com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the fleſh, is there meant by Doctrine: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:110647:31"/> being ſo comprehenſive a word, that it contains in it no leſs (if not more) than the foundation-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rt, mentioned <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. And therefore they that tranſgreſs, and abide not in that fundamental part, <hi>viz.</hi> Repentance, Faith, the Doctrine of Baptiſms, Laying on of Hands, the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Dead, and eternal Judgment, have not God as his Church; but he that continues in the Doctrine of Chriſt, hath both the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Son.</p>
               <p>Then is it no abuſe of the Text, to ſay as the Text ſaith: But you rather abuſe us, to ſay that we infer that there can be no Churches nor Church-Members, that continue not in every thing that Chriſt taught; and that they have not God, nor are no Members of Chriſt. But we ſay, They cannot be Churches rightly conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, that abide not in Chriſts Doctrine, for they have not God, and ſo ſaith the Text. And yet there may be Churches truly ſtated, that are not perfect, and that will not ſay, they have no ſin: <hi>For in many things we offend all,</hi> James 3.2.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 21.</head>
               <p>If you ſhall ſay, That by denying Communion to thoſe that abide not in the Doctrine of Christ, you mean ſuch as abide not in Fundamentals; not but that you could have Communion with thoſe that err and differ from you in the Circumſtantials of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as ſome of you have ſaid, and others have
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:110647:32"/> printed: Then we demand, what thoſe Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tial Errors are? And whether they are not tran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>greſſions of the Word, Doctrine, Sayings, Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mands, or Oracles of Chriſt? If they be tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſions of the Sayings and Oracles of Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we demand whether that argument is not ridiculou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that ſaith, They have no communion with God, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> abide not in all the Sayings and Doctrines of Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>&amp;c?</hi> And then what becomes of your great cry y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> make against us, for not continuing in all the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctrines and Sayings of Chriſt; and that whoev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> doth not continue in all, hath no communion wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God? when your ſelves allow there may be commu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nion where Errors are circumſtantial, and there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tacitly acknowledge what other whiles you oppoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>(viz.)</hi> That they that abide in all Chriſts Doctrin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may notwithſtanding have communion with God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We have already told you, That no know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Error ought to be ſuffered in the Church; no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> do we ſay we can have communion with thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that maintain any thing contrary, or in oppo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſition to the Doctrine of Chriſt: Yet as you ſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we can have communion with thoſe that diffe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from us in Circumſtantials; but to give ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſelves or others an allowance to err in Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals, would be a crime as bad, as an allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in any fleſhly and actual ſin.</p>
               <p n="2">2. You then demand what thoſe Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantials are, and whether they be not tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:110647:32"/> of the Word, Sayings, Doctrine, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, or Oracles of Chriſt; we ſay no, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re not tranſgreſſions againſt Chriſts Doctrine, &amp;c. but ſuch things as may be done, or left <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndone, and no ſin committed againſt God. But ſay you, what are thoſe Errors? It is an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rror to refuſe and deny the eating of meats, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecauſe <hi>every creature of God is good, and nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o be refuſed, if it be received with thanksgiving:</hi> Yet if my Brother be weak, and will eat herbs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd will be offended if I eat fleſh, we will not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reak communion with him becauſe he will eat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o fleſh, nor eat fleſh our ſelves, leſt we cauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r weak Brother to ſtumble and be offended; this is to err in circumſtantials, and all other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hings of the like kind, that may, or may not be done, and no Law of Chriſt broken; for tranſgreſſions of the Word and Doctrine of Chriſt, muſt not be tollerated in the Church of Chriſt, he muſt be heard in all things; and if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o, that Argument is not ridiculous, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ains firm and untouched, that ſaith, They <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ve not God as his Church, who tranſgreſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd abide not in the Doſtrine of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And then that great cry (as you call it) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e make againſt you, for your diſobedience to Chriſt, is ſtill remaining where it was; our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oices will be lifted up as high as ever, until <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou do from the heart obey that form of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which was delivered to the Primitive
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:110647:33"/> Saints, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.17. nor do we allow Communi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on where Errors are (except you mean ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is above expreſſed) longer than the erronio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> can be orderly dealt with; therefore we do no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tacitly acknowledge (as you imagine) wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> other-while we oppoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 22.</head>
               <p>But if you ſhall ſay, you intend by Chriſts Do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctrine thoſe ſix Principles contained, <hi>Heb. 6.</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that whoever agrees with you in them, doth agr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in fundamentals, and with ſuch you can communi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cate: then we demand why ſome of you refuſe com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>munion about an Oath, others about mixt Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riages, others about waſhing of Feet; others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you refuſe communion with ſuch as are under layin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on of Hands, if they do hold communion with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that are not under laying on of Hands; others re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fuſe communion in matters of Apparel; others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bout Blood and things ſtrangled? What reaſon ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you for theſe diviſions, unleſs you will ſay, all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> are Fundamentals; and if they be, then what a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> your circumſtantials you talk of? and whether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> have not adopted more Fundamentals than ever yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> found in the 6th of the <hi>Hebrews?</hi> And wheth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> you may not by the ſame reaſon, if that Notion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſts not taking fleſh of the Virgin, get but Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelytes enough; adopt that alſo into the number <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Fundamentals, as well as the reſt? and ſo at l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> leave us no circumſtantials to differ about; for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> can well remember, when laying on of Hands w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:110647:33"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot eſteemed a Fundamental Doctrine, but the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ractiſers of it, for ſome time, kept their commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with us, till it had made a Party, and then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> was advanced to the dignity of Fundamental, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd afterwards we were eſteemed too mean to keep <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mpany with thoſe that ſo eſteemed it; and have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all the fore-mentioned Opinions, bid fair for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me advancement? and will they not be ſo eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when they which are the Abettors of them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hink they have numbers and opportunities for that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rpoſe?</p>
               <p>And may they not by the ſame arguments which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> uſe to ſeparate from us, ſeparate from you, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ey believe any thing to be a Doctrine of Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich you do not?</p>
               <p>And do you not by this means furniſh men with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eapons to divide Churches into Atoms, till they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ve made Gods ſpiritual Houſe like his literal Houſe, that ſhall not have one Stone left upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which will not be thrown down? Will they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t argue thus: They which abide not in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>trine of Chriſt, have not God; but ſuch as are not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or waſhing of feet, ſaluting with a holy kiſs, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ch as are for taking an Oath, though to end ſtrife, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for eating of Blood, and things ſtrangled, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch as being under laying on of hands, yet commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with them that are not under it; together <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th ſuch as do not eat a Supper before breaking of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ead, and ſuch as marry out of the Church, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ch as believe Christ took fleſh of the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:110647:34"/> all theſe do not abide in the Doctrine of Chriſt, and therefore they have not God? Where will not this kind of reaſoning run you at laſt?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. You know we ſay and do intend by Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Doctrine, thoſe ſix Principles mentioned <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. and that whoever agrees with us in Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, we can have Communion with, provided their Converſation be according to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We refuſe communion with thoſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> take ſome Oaths, becauſe Chriſt doth forbid ſuch ſwearing, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.12. and alſo becauſe ſuch as take them, abjure their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Chriſt, and ſwear obedience to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Doctrines and Commandments of men.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We refuſe communion about mixt Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, becauſe they are forbid both in the Ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and New Teſtament: The Church of <hi>Pergam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> muſt not have them among them that hold ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Doctrine.</p>
               <p n="4">4. We know of none that refuſe communic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> about waſhing of Feet.</p>
               <p n="5">5. We refuſe communion with thoſe that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> under laying on of hands, if they have commu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nion with thoſe that are not under laying on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hands; becauſe it is diſorder and confuſion, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alſo a tranſgreſſion againſt the Doctrine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="6">6. We do not refuſe communion in matte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:110647:34"/> of Apparel, otherwiſe than is ſaid in the An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwer to the fourth Queſtion.</p>
               <p n="7">7. There is ſufficient ground to deal with ſuch Members as will eat Blood, and things ſtrangled, to the trouble and offence of their fellow-Brethren, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.29. &amp; 21.25. for we would have you to know that Members of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches may hold that in their Judgments and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, and that in their Lives, though they are under all the firſt Principles of the Oracles of God, that may deſerve the cenſure of the Church, and yet the Church not adopt them firſt Rudiments of Chriſtianity; for we have no Fundamentals adopted by us, nor do we own more than thoſe <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. for all this taunting Talk of yours: And yet we ſhall ſay, That there is good reaſon why we ſhould differ with thoſe that deny the Doctrine of the Trinity, and that Chriſt is the ſecond Perſon in it, God of one ſubſtance with the Father; yea, and refuſe communion with them that ſay he is a crea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed Being, and was not, nor had no being, before he was conceived in the Womb of the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> and indeed this wicked and abſurd opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion did get Proſelytes, and found opportunity to make a Schiſm in the Body of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Your memory fails you, as well as you ſay you can remember; for we can better know and remember that before we came under laying on of hands, we did eſteem it a Foundation-Principle,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:110647:35"/> and ſubmitted to it, as to one; but did indeed keep and continue with you for ſome time, preaching, diſputing, and perſwading you to obey the Lord Jeſus, (but other communion we had none) until many of you were harden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and believed not; but ſpake evil of this way before the multitude; then we departed, and ſeparated the Diſciples.</p>
               <p n="9">9. There is none, by our Arguments we have to ſeparate from you, can ſeparate from us; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we ſtill continue, through the grace of God, in the Doctrine of Chriſt; nor ſay things are of the Doctrine of Chriſt, that are not. Nor do we, by what means we take to defend that Truth which you oppoſe, put Weapons in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of any to divide Churches; but the means you take to reſiſt the Truth, will furniſh thoſe that liſt to make uſe of them wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Weapons to fill the Church with Error and Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> till it becomes as filthy as <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Therefore though you would argue u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> falſly into great inconveniencies, we may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it upon your ſelves from what you maintain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and argue thus: If communion may be hel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with them that diſown the practice of laying on of hands, then with them that diſown anothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Principle of the Doctrine of Chriſt, and ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> third, and them that adore two Gods, the tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God and a dumb Idol; ſinful Marriages; th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt is a meer created man, and onely a Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:110647:35"/> made, as <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>David</hi> was; and ſinful ſwearing: Then may we not break communion, though all <hi>Rome</hi>'s traſh and filth ſhould be brought in. And where will this kind of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning run you at laſt?</p>
               <p>Here ends their Queſtions grounded upon their ſecond <hi>Hypotheſis:</hi> The third follows, with our Anſwers to them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 23.</head>
               <p>But if you ſhall ſay, Laying on of hands is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned by the Scripture, <hi>Heb. 6.</hi> to be a Doctrine of Chriſt, and a Foundation-Doctrine, and therefore though ſome Opinions may be called Foundation-Doctrines, without warrant; yet that doth not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but you may call a Doctrine ſo, when you have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Warrant, as you have for this; and therefore if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> differ from you in denying a Fundamental Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, you can have no communion with us:</p>
               <p>We demand, How you can infallibly infer your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ractice from this Text, <hi>Heb. 6.</hi> if you do but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>der first, That there are many learned men of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who though they practiſe lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> on of hands upon all their Members, as you do: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as you, ſo they uſe their endeavours to prove <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h a practice from hence; yet Dr. <hi>Hamond,</hi> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>arned and Judicious as moſt of that Way, and as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> read in the Cuſtoms of the Primitive Times, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> us in his Annotations upon that place, that the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:110647:36"/> laying on of hands there ſpoken of, is underſtood for a laying on of hands upon ſuch as had fallen after Baptiſm, which was done to ſignifie their Reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Church. And this he further proves from <hi>Paul</hi>'s advice to <hi>Timothy, 1 Tim. 5.22.</hi> where he is not ſpeaking of any other thing, but Church-Cenſures; as how that an Elder ſhould not be accuſed, but by two or three Witneſſes, <hi>verſ. 19.</hi> that thoſe that ſin ſhould be rebuked before all, <hi>ver. 20.</hi> and that he ſhould not in judging Offenders, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> any thing by partiality, <hi>verſ. 21.</hi> neither lay o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hands too ſuddenly upon any that had been cenſure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by the Church, and had not truly repented of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſins; leſt he thereby became partaker of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſins, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>We from hence demand, Which of all theſe la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ying on of hands is intended <hi>Heb. 6.</hi> and is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which you call a Doctrine of Christ? And whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther (if the laying on of hands ſpoken of <hi>Heb. 6.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a Doctrine of Chriſt) it is not more ſafe to under<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtand it for that Doctrine which Chriſt preached <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> practiſed, and his Apoſtles afterwards practiſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> healing the Sick, than for thoſe other laying o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hands, which Chriſt never taught nor practiſed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which the Apoſtles never practiſed in conformit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a Command, but by way of Accommodation to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> laudable Cuſtoms of the Jews, as they did in di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> other Caſes; and if they did practiſe that o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> laying on of hands, <hi>Acts 8. &amp; 19.</hi> in obedien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a Command, ſhew thoſe Commands; and alſo
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:110647:36"/> your practice of laying on of hands on all you bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, both Men and Women, who have no ſuch Bleſſing to communicate as they had, doth agree with their practice, and we ſhall be ſatisfied.</p>
               <p>And ſince we read of divers laying on of hands, and divers men are differently perſwaded concerning that in <hi>Heb. 16.</hi> yea, and ſuch men whoſe interest leads them to think of it as you do; and yet they cannot reaſonably ſo underſtand it; we demand, Whether this is not a ſufficient ground for us to doubt whether the laying on of hands practiſed by you, be inſtituted by God? Whether it can reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably and infallibly be inferred from this Text? And if not, whether it be not great preſumption for you to judge all incommunicable, that come not up to you in a matter that is ſo dubitable.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Never put an <hi>if</hi> to it, for we do ſay, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands, mentioned <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. is one Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of the firſt Oracles of God, and of the Doctrine of Chriſt, one of the firſt Rudiments <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Chriſtianity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> You then demand, How <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>om this Text, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. we can infallibly infer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur practice? Conſidering Dr. <hi>Hamond,</hi> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>earned and Judicious as any in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and as well read in the Cuſtoms of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rimitive Times, tells us in his Annotations <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on that place <hi>That the laying on of hands there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ken of, is underſtood for a laying on of hands up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſuch as had fallen after Baptiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:110647:37"/> 2. It's notably done, and well thought on, ſeeing help fails you from the Scriptures, to ſee whether the learned judicious and well-read Doctors in Myſtery <hi>Babylon,</hi> can lend you any<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But pray doth not this learned, judicious, and well-read Doctor, tell you no where, in no place of his Annotations, <hi>That the baptiſing of Infants was a primitive Practice, or that it came in near thoſe Times by good, authentick, Orthodox Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity?</hi> If he doth, pray do you conſider how you can infallibly infer from <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of Believers, as you practiſe it, ſince ſo learned a judicious and well-read Doctor was in his Judgement and Practice for ſprinkling of Babes; and no doubt but he (ſo learned and wiſe) hath ſomething to ſay for his Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>But this</hi> (ſay you) <hi>he further proves fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Paul's advice to Timothy,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.2. <hi>where he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not ſpeaking of any other thing but Church-Cen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſures.</hi> Look again the whole Chapter thorow, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that a Church-Cenſure? v. 18, 19. if not, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that, v. 22. may not be a laying on of hands ſud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>denly upon any that had been cenſured by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And this will appear more plain, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> comparing the third Chapter with this; the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may it be as fairly and as wiſely conclude<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> That this laying on of hands which <hi>Timothy</hi> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> not be ſudden in, was for Ordination of <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> rather than a laying on of han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:110647:37"/> upon ſuch as had fallen after Baptiſm: for where read you of ſuch a laying on of hands in all the Scripture, either taught or practiſed by any; the deep ſilence thereof, makes us we can neither credit the Doctor nor you in this matter, though he be learned, judicious, and well read in the Primitive Cuſtoms. But if what he ſaith were true, yet will it do you no ſervice; becauſe if ſuch a laying on of hands were then practiſed, neither you nor Dr. <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> to help you, (nay, take <hi>Victor,</hi> and the third Council of <hi>Carthage</hi> with you alſo) can prove ſuch a laying on of hands to be that men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. which is there ſaid to be a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of the Doctrine of Chriſt, a Foundation-Principle. But no more in this place to ſuch a Scriptureleſs-notion.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To your ſecond conſideration, we ſhall ſay no more yet, than what we have already ſaid in anſwer to your former printed Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, where this is ſtated, and by us anſwered. See <hi>Gods Oracle and Chriſts Doctrine,</hi> p. 39, 40. But we grant,</p>
               <p>You do read of a laying on of hands on the Sick, but how delivered in the Commiſſion, we ſhall hereafter examine: And you do read of laying on of hands to ordain Officers, and of laying on of hands by which men received the extraordinary Gifts of the Spirit: But why do you not make up juſt half a dozen, but leave out
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:110647:38"/> that now, you brought in with the reſt in your printed Queſtions before; mentioned <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.12. <hi>But the fifth</hi> (you ſay) <hi>is that laying on of hands which was afterwards call'd Confirmation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> becauſe by the Gifts of the holy Ghoſt, the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were confirmed in the truth of the Goſpel: and though thoſe Gifts ceaſed, yet they continued the practice of it in the Church of Rome, and many other Proteſtant Churches to this day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Here you confeſs that the laying on of hands mentioned in <hi>Act.</hi> 18.17. &amp; 19.6. is pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and many Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Churches, down from the primitive times to this day. May we not think it ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ge, if it be ſo, that you ſhould oppoſe and refuſe to practiſe that which ſo many learned, judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and well-read Doctors as have been all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and many Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Churches, do practiſe; but rather againſt many, take the private opinion of ſome few, who by their opinion (if true) do not contradict nor oppoſe that laying on of hands mentioned by you in the fifth of your numerations; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering withall, that the Doctors in <hi>Rome,</hi> and in many Proteſtant Churches, do not conſent to ſuch a practice as laying on of hands, when they receive any that are fallen after Baptiſm, at this day.</p>
               <p n="6">6. In your next, you ſeem to thruſt in by head and ſhoulders, another ſort of laying on
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:110647:38"/> of hands; or if not, another ground the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>les and primitive Churches had to practiſe the former you numerate, than the Authority of Chriſts Doctrine, when you ſay, <hi>It was practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by them, by way of accomodation to the Jewiſh Cuſtoms; as</hi> (you ſay) <hi>appears in Moſes laying his hands upon Joſhua,</hi> Numb. 18.19, 22, 23. Deut. 34.9. <hi>and ſo Jacob bleſſed the Children of Joſeph, by laying his hands upon them.</hi> Doth it appear from thoſe places and paſſages you quote, that the Apoſtles and primitive Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es did practiſe laying on of hands by way of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation to the Jewiſh Cuſtoms? We think when you conſider better what you ſay, you will not be of that mind: For, may it not is well be concluded, That the Apoſtles practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Baptiſm of Water by way of Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to the Jewiſh Cuſtoms, as appears, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Jews among their Cuſtoms had divers waſhings, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.10. And is not this as good a proof of the one, as yours is of the other?</p>
               <p n="7">7. And what though the people brought their Children to Chriſt for him to bleſs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.13. in obſervation of a Jewiſh Cuſtom, and the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the Synagogue did the like? <hi>Mark</hi> 5.23. And what if it ſhould be granted that Chriſt did lay his hands on them to confer Bleſſings on the one, and to heal the other, by way of Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation to the Jewiſh Cuſtoms? Will it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:110647:39"/> therefore that his Apoſtles after his paſſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> when he had blotted out the hand-writing o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ordinances, nailing them to his Croſs, <hi>Col.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 14. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.15. and after his Reſurrection, when he had given them their Commiſſion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. yea, and after he was aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and had ſent them, according to his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, the Spirit of Truth, which ſhould guide them into all Truth, ſhould practiſe laying on of hands by way of Accommodation to the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Cuſtoms, and call it a Principle of Chriſts Doctrine, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. Surely no man in his right mind, will ſo conclude. But leaving this too, as a Scriptureleſs-notion, we will proceed.</p>
               <p n="8">8. You then demand, <hi>Which of all theſe lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings on of hands is intended</hi> Heb. 6. <hi>and is that which we call a Doctrine of Christ?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You have been told long ſince, which lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands is intended <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. that it is that practiſed by the Apoſtles, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.17. &amp; 19.6. for which let the Reader conſult <hi>Gods Oracle, and Chriſts Doctrine,</hi> from page 41. to page 54. where this Queſtion is ſtated by you, and anſwered, yea, and clearly proved to be that laying on of hands on baptiſed Believers as ſuch, and no other.</p>
               <p n="9">9. But then you enquire, <hi>Whether it be not more ſafe to understand it for that Doctrine which Chriſt preached and practiſed, and his Apoſtles af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards practiſed in healing the Sick, than that
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:110647:39"/> Chriſt never taught nor practiſed, nor his Apoſtles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>either, in conformity to a Command, but by way of accommodation to the laudable Custom of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ews, as they did in divers other Caſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We confeſs, it is more ſafe, of the two, to underſtand it to be for healing the Sick, than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat which Chriſt never taught nor practis'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or his Apoſtles neither, in conformity to a Command, if any ſuch laying on of hands there is; which if there be, we know of none, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cept it be that laying on of hands mentioned <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.12. which not they, but the wicked practiſed.</p>
               <p>But 'tis obſervable how rarely well you beg <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Queſtion, when you conclude that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles did in divers caſes practiſe laying on of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nds by way of Accommodation to the lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Cuſtom of the Jews: Pray where is that written? There is not the leaſt ſyllable in the Scripture that intimates ſuch a thing, much leſs that affirms it.</p>
               <p n="10">10. And whereas you require us, <hi>if they did practiſe that laying on of hands,</hi> Act. 8.17. &amp; 19. <hi>in obedience to a Command, to ſhew it.</hi> We ſay it hath been already ſhewed. Let the <hi>Reader</hi> peruſe <hi>Gods Oracle and Chriſts Doctrine,</hi> from page 79. to page 84. And as for our practice of laying on of hands on all we baptiſe, both Men and Women, that hath been ſhewed and proved alſo: Let the Reader ſee <hi>Gods Oracle
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:110647:40"/> and Christs Doctrine,</hi> page 47, 48, 49. Read an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> weigh well what is there ſaid, without partiali<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty, laying aſide all prejudicate Opinions an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> byaſſed Reſolutions, and he will be ſatisfied i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> both.</p>
               <p n="11">11. But you further ſay, <hi>Since divers men an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> differently perſwaded concerning that in</hi> Heb. 6. <hi>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> and ſuch men whoſe interest leads them to think o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it as we do, and yet they cannot reaſonably ſo under<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stand it; you demand whether this is not a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent ground for you to doubt whether the layin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> on of hands practiſed by us, be inſtitued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Truly we think it ſo far from being a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent ground for you to doubt, becauſe Dr. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mond,</hi> or any other learned judicious Doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> doth, that we think it is not any ground at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for you to doubt alſo: We have abler (an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more approved) Doctors for our practice, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Dr. <hi>Hamond,</hi> or <hi>Victor,</hi> or <hi>Carthage</hi>'s Councils<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And therefore we ſay it can be both reaſonabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and infallibly inferred, and more than an inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence it is from <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. comparing this Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> with ſome other, that the laying on of hands <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> practiſe, is inſtituted by the Lord, as a Found<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion-Principle of Chriſts Doctrine; ans is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> preſumption to judge you incommunicable that come not up to us in a matter not dubin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, but clear and plain.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="question">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:110647:40"/>
               <head>Queſt. 24.</head>
               <p>And whereas you ſay thoſe Doctrines are call'd beginning Doctrines, <hi>Heb. 6.</hi> and therefore laying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n of hands muſt be ſo call'd:</p>
               <p>We demand, Why the Wonders which the Apoſtles did, &amp; the Cures they wrought by laying on of hands upon ſuch as they healed, being that which Christ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aught, and himſelf and Apoſtles practiſed, might not rather be esteemed a beginning of the Doctrine of Chriſt, than that which you practiſe, for which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u have at beſt but a doubtful example? And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hough this of healing was practicable upon none but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon the Sick, yet was it teaching to all, to ſee and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ear the Sick were raiſed and cured; as appears <hi>Luk. 13.47. Act. 28.8, 9.</hi> and ſo it was a practice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at was introductive to the beginnings of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in thoſe times.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. You demand, Why the Wonders which the Apoſtles did, and the Cures they wrought, by laying on of hands upon ſuch as they healed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing that which Chriſt taught, and himſelf and the Apoſtles practiſed, might not rather be eſteemed a beginning of the Doctrine of Chriſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>an that which we practiſe?</p>
               <p>The laying on of hands to heal the Sick, was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot preceptively taught by Chriſt, but promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>vely, in the way of a Promiſe annexed and made to them that did believe; <hi>Theſe ſigns ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ollow them that believe,</hi> Mark 16.17. <hi>They ſhall
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:110647:41"/> lay hands on the Sick, and they ſhall recover,</hi> verſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 18. By which ſignes the preceptive part of Chriſts Word and Doctrine was confirmed to be from Heaven, and not of Men; <hi>And they wen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> forth and preached every where, the Lord working with them, confirming the Word with ſigns follow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing, Amen,</hi> verſ. 20. Then laying on of hands to heal the Sick, not being preceptively taught by Chriſt, by way of command, but promiſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by way of Promiſe, it cannot be eſteemed that laying on of hands, which is a Principle o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Doctrine of Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. now under de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, but that by which that Principle of Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beginning Word or Doctrine, was (among the reſt of them) confirmed to be from Heaven, and not of men.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Again, If laying on of hands to heal the Sick, was preceptively taught, by way of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and ſo ought to be eſteemed that part of the beginning Doctrine of Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Then is caſting out <hi>Devils,</hi> ſpeaking with new <hi>Tongues,</hi> taking up <hi>Serpents,</hi> drinking any <hi>dead <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thing</hi> and not be hurt, taught alſo by way o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Command; and then every one of them is a well the beginning Doctrine of Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and your duty to do, as to be baptiſed: An <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> why then ſhould not caſting out <hi>Devils,</hi> and every one of the reſt be eſteemed a Principle i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſts Doctrine, and the firſt Rudiments o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſtianity? We have then better Reaſon tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:110647:41"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny you have to the contrary to eſteem laying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n of hands on baptiſed Believers as ſuch, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tiſed by the Apoſtles, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.17. <hi>Act.</hi> 19.6. to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e one Principle of the beginning Doctrine of Chriſt, rather than that to heal the Sick, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was promiſſively and not preceptively <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aught by Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But you ſay, <hi>Rather to heal the Sick, than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat we practiſe, for which we have but a doubtful Example at the beſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How can you be ſo clouded, as to ſay, We <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave for laying on of hands but a doubtful Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample at the beſt? What practice can have more clear and apparant example than we have for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urs? See <hi>Act</hi> 8.17. &amp; 19.6. Moreover it's one of the firſt Principles of the Oracles of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12. One of the Principles of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt, a Foundation-principle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2. Authority enough to all that have reaſon, and will uſe it, whoſe minds are not darkened.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And as you ſay, ſo we ſay, <hi>This laying on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f hands to heal the Sick, was practicable to none out the Sick:</hi> But how then could it be one of the firſt Rudiments of Chriſtianity, when no Chriſtian Man or Woman could be built upon this Foundation, except he or ſhe were firſt ſick, and then you may eſteem Sickneſs to be a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to this foundation, and ſo rather a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Doctrine of Chriſt. But you ſay, <hi>It was teaching to all:</hi> And we ſay, So it was pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:110647:42"/> on all; and therefore it cannot be the be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginning Doctrine of Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. becau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they laid on hands to heal the Sick that were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Church-Members, but of the world, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 11, 12, 13. <hi>Act.</hi> 28.7, 8, 9. <hi>The Lord working wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> them, confirming the Word with ſigns following</hi> according to <hi>Mark</hi> 16.20.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 25.</head>
               <p>But whereas you ſay, Laying on of hands is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Foundation-Doctrine, or a part of the Foundation of Chriſtianity, and therefore you cannot communi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cate with ſuch as do not own it; We demand whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Text ſaith any ſuch thing? And wheth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> there can be any other Foundation laid, than th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which is laid, which is Jeſus Chriſt? <hi>1 Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 11, 12.</hi> —</p>
               <p>And we demand, whether this be not the ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> words and ſence of the Text, when the Autho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſays, <hi>Heb. 6.</hi> he <hi>would not lay again the Foun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dation OF Repentance, and the Foundation OF Faith, and the Foundation OF the Doctrine o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Baptiſm, and the Foundation OF laying on o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hands,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>From all which we demand, Whether this pra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctice of yours, in laying on of hands upon all Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Diſciples, (though it ſhould be intended in Heb. <hi>6.</hi> which we deſpair of ever ſeeing the proof of) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Doctrine or Principle without which Gods Houſe cannot be, or a Doctrine or Principle without which it cannot ſo well and ſo compleatly be? If you ſay, It
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:110647:42"/> is that without which Gods Houſe cannot be; prove it, and we will believe you: But if you ſay, God may have a Houſe, though leſs perfect, without it; then are not you all guilty of Schiſm in making a Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from it?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Your demand here is, <hi>Where the Text ſaith the laying on of hands is a Foundation-Doctrine, or a part of the Foundation of Chriſtianity?</hi> Oh ſtrange! Are you ſtill ignorant of that, not-withſtanding one of you confeſſed it to be one of the firſt Rudiments of Chriſtianity, &amp; ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the practice of it? It is to be feared he did not lye to men but God, when he ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed and practiſed; and yet ſecretly and men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally reſerve, That it was no part of the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Chriſtianity; as he here doth not only query, but plainly affirm. But we will gratifie you once more, and tell you, That Text <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2. ſaith, <hi>Not laying again the Foundation of —laying on of hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Then you demand, <hi>Whether there can be any other Foundation laid, than that which is laid, Which is Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> And go from querying to arguing; being put to this lamentable and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate ſtraight, that rather than you will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge laying on of hands to be a foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on-Principle, you will deny Repentance, Faith, the Doctrine of Baptiſms, the Reſurrection of the Dead, and eternal Judgement, to be a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:110647:43"/> or any part of the foundation of Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtianity: for it appears by your argument that you hold that it is no part of the foundatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Chriſtianity to repent and confeſs our ſins and to believe in Chriſt for the pardon of them nor no part of the foundation of Chriſtianity t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be baptiſed in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to practiſe Prayer, with laying on of hands, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we might receive the Spirit; to which end lay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing on of hands was and is practiſed, that eve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry Member might be baptiſed by that one Spiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into one Body; nor no part of the Foundatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Chriſtianity to believe the Reſurrection o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Dead, and eternal Judgement. And pray, ſeeing the Spirit in <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2. ſaith they ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Foundations, (for thus you and we read, <hi>No laying again the foundation of Repentance from dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> works, and Faith towards God, the Doctrine of Bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſms, and of laying on of Hands, and of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Dead, and of eternal Judgement</hi>) and they be (as you ſay) no part of the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſtianity, what are they the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of then? Judaiſm, or Paganiſm? For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> foundation they are, and we relieve of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity. But you thus reaſon:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If there can be no other foundation than Jeſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſt, then is not Faith, nor Repentance, nor Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands, nor the believing the Reſurrectio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the Dead, nor eternal Judgement, a foundatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> or part of the foundation of Christianity. But
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:110647:43"/> there can be no other foundation laid than Jeſus Christ. Ergo, Repentance, Faith, Baptiſm, and Laying on of hands, the belief of the Reſurrection of the Dead, and eternal Judgement, cannot be a foundation, or part of the foundation of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We deny the conſequence of your major Propoſition: For all theſe that you ſay cannot be a foundation, nor no part of the Foundation of Chriſtianity, the Spirit of God ſaith they are Foundation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. and the Spirit tels the <hi>Epheſians</hi> they were <hi>built upon the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Apoſtles and Prophets, Jeſus Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf being the chief Corner-ſtone,</hi> Epheſ. 2.20. And were they not built on that foundation as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians? If they were built thereon as Chriſtians, which you cannot deny, then ſure that founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was part of the foundation of Chriſtianity, which foundation is not another, but the ſame mentioned <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Nor will your next Argument prove your major: For though Chriſt be the foundation of all thoſe Duties, as the Author, the great Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor and Teacher of them, and the chief Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner-ſtone; yet doth it not follow; but that theſe Duties be the Principles of his Doctrine, and the Foundation of Chriſtianity; being in plain terms ſaid to be ſo by the Spirit of God, in the fore-cited places.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Neither doth this hinder but that Chriſt is the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:110647:44"/> Foundation, and that other foundation can no man lay, than Chriſt; which thoſe do, who from the heart obey this form of Doctrine, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.17. for by Repentance we ſee our wretched and undone condition without Chriſt; by Eaith we ſee our ſins pardoned, out perſons juſtified and accepted by Chriſt; by being baptiſed into his Name, we actually acknowledge his Death for our ſins, and a waſhing of them away, and that he is riſen, and we with him, to newneſs of life; by prayer and laying on of hands, we wait therein upon God, for the Spirit which he promiſed to ſend from the Father, <hi>John</hi> 15.26. by which we are all baptiſed into his Body, and have the witneſs in our ſelves, that we are the Children of God; by the belief of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Body, we wait in hope of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, and acknowledge that Chriſt is riſen, and is the Reſurrection and the Life; and that we ſhall, though dead, be raiſed up to life by him at the laſt day; and by the belief of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Judgement, we look for his coming to judge both the Dead and the Living; and that we ſhall all appear before the Judgement-Seat of Chriſt, and there receive according to the things done in our Body, whether they be good or bad, with the Reward either of eternal Joy, or everlaſting ſhame and contempt. So that in deed, he that builds not upon theſe foundation-Principles, lays not Chriſt the foundation, not
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:110647:44"/> can he be a Chriſtian. So inſeparable is Chriſt and theſe Principles of his Doctrine, that he cannot be laid the Foundation without theſe are laid, nor can theſe be laid the foundation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt; for had not Chriſt been a Prince and a Saviour, able to ſave all that come unto God by him, there had been no foundation for theſe. And whoſo ſhall refuſe to ſubmit to theſe, as the Principles of his Doctrine, Chriſt will be no Saviour to them. And this is the very ſence of the Text, to which the whole body of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture agrees and conſents: for the Apoſtle doth not deny Chriſt to be the Foundation, when he ſaith theſe Principles of his Doctrine are; nor doth he deny theſe are, when he ſaith Chriſt is, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11, 12. as you abſurdly argue. And who knows not, that knows any thing in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, that he that falls away from one of theſe foundation-Principles, <hi>viz.</hi> the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Dead, falls from Chriſt, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies him to be the foundation: <hi>If Chriſt be not riſen, your faith is vain, you are yet in your ſins,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.17. Then thoſe cannot be denied to be the foundation, but Chriſt muſt be denied alſo.</p>
               <p n="5">5. But then when you leave arguing, and query again, Whether this be not the ſence of the Text, when the Author ſays, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. <hi>he would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lay again the foundation of Repentance, and the foundation of Faith, and the foundation of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:110647:45"/> of Baptiſms, and the foundation of Laying on of hands, &amp;c.</hi> Here now you ſay the Author himſelf ſays theſe are the foundation, as ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and as confidently as you denied them ſo to be before; and theſe he ſaith he will not lay again, <hi>Not laying again the foundation of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, &amp;c. Heb.</hi> 6.1. but will go on to perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; though we doubt not but he intended no leſs but that Chriſt was the chief Corner-ſtone, the foundation of all theſe Principles and firſt Rudiments of Chriſtianity. He then concludes that they ought not to lay the foundation again, but to leave them, and to go on to perfection; and if they did not go on unto perfection; but fall from the foundation they had laid, there would be no renewing them again unto Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, no laying the foundation the ſecond time.</p>
               <p>And then you argue again, <hi>If then the faith and obedience mentioned</hi> Heb. 6. <hi>be the Gold, Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and precious Stones, that we build upon this foundation, according to</hi> 1 Cor. 3.12. <hi>and not the foundation it ſelf,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If it be as you ſay, is not laying on of hands, which is among them, neither Gold, Silver, nor a precious Stone? If not, it muſt be Wood, Hay, Stubble; and yet you ſay the Author of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſays it is a Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but it is the Foundation, we ſay, with Jeſus Chriſt, himſelf being the Chief Corner-ſtone
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:110647:45"/> on which the Chriſtian Church is built, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.20. Then it follows, except this foundation be laid, all and every part of it, the Houſe can never be; though where the foundation is laid, there are other things without which the Houſe may be, though not ſo well and compleatly be. And in like manner we ſay, This Foundation <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. and every Principle of it, the belief and practice of, is abſolutely neceſſary to the being of Gods Houſe; and yet there are other things, the belief and practice of, is neceſſary to the further edification of Gods Houſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, it cannot ſo well be. And ſince here we ſeem in ſome ſort to agree, you had done well if you had told us what in your opinion thoſe things are, without which the Houſe of God can never be; ſeeing you ſay that Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are no parts of the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſtianity; and how Chriſt can be laid the Foundation, and thoſe Principles and Foundations mentioned <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. neither believed nor practiſed.</p>
               <p>But not to dwell any longer on this, our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to your laſt demand in this Queſtion, is, That the Houſe cannot be, except the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be laid in whole, not in part; and laying on of hands on all baptiſed Diſciples, being one Principle of the Foundation, muſt be neceſſary to its being; without which, a Church rightly conſtituted can never be. And this we have
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:110647:46"/> proved, whether you will believe it, or no. And therefore we are not guilty of Schiſm in making a Separation from you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 26.</head>
               <p>We demand, Why that laying on of hands, <hi>Heb. 6.</hi> which you ſay is called a foundation, may not be figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively underſtood for the holy Spirit which was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thereby, and which they were ſaid to partake of, <hi>verſ. 4.</hi> the Gift whereof was a great ſupport to the profeſſion of the Chriſtian Faith, and for that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the Doctrine of the Spirit might there be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood for one of the Doctrines of Chriſt, which he taught his Diſciples once and again, before his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture from them? We demand why may not this be ſo, ſince the Scripture doth uſually ſpeak after this manner, putting the Cup for the Wine contained in it; and the Bread and Wine, for the Body and Blood of Christ, which are but the means by which the Body and Blood of Chriſt are commemorated; in like manner men are ſaid to be Enemies to the Croſs of Christ, when they ſlight thoſe advantages that acrue to the world, which he obtained by his ſuffering thereupon? And whether that laying on of hands, <hi>Heb. 6.</hi> may not by the ſame figure of ſpeaking, be put for the reception of the Spirit, which was ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the firſt eſtabliſhing a Chriſtian Church? <hi>Heb. 2.3, 4. How ſhall we eſcape, if we neglect ſo great Salvation, which at the firſt began to be ſpoken by the Lord, and was confirmed unto us by them that heard him? God alſo bearing them
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:110647:46"/> witneſs, both with ſigns and wonders, and with divers miracles and gifts of the holy Ghoſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his own will.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Before you ſaid, <hi>Laying on of hands was no foundation;</hi> and now here you demand, <hi>Why that laying on of hands,</hi> Heb. 6. <hi>which we ſay is called a Foundation, may not figuratively be underſtood for the holy Spirit that was given thereby?</hi> We perceive you would be content it ſhould be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or any thing, but what it is ſaid by the Spirit of God to be.</p>
               <p>And again, you demand, <hi>Why this may not be ſo, ſeeing the Scripture doth uſually ſpeak after this manner; putting the Cup for the Wine contained in it; and the Bread and Wine, for the Body and Blood of Chriſt, which are but the means by which the Body and Blood of Chriſt are commemorated?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Well, for Argument-ſake, what if we ſhould ſay it may be ſo underſtood? We hope you will not ſay, Though we are to take the Wine for the Cup, that the Cup is not by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution to be uſed, as a decent and neceſſary means to convey the Wine to our mouths, that ſo we may drink the Wine: And ſo though the Bread and Wine be taken for the Body and Blood of Chriſt, and are but the means to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorate his Body and Blood; yet we hope you will allow us to uſe the Bread and Wine, as the means to commemorate the Lords Body and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:110647:47"/> Blood, and not reject it, and caſt it off as uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs. So in like manner, if laying on of hands be a figurative ſpeech, and underſtood for the Spirit that was given thereby; we hope you muſt allow that laying on of hands ought to be uſed and practiſed, as the means by which the Spirit was obtained, and is given, as well as you will the Cup, and the Bread and Wine, in your figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative inſtances, and we deſire no more.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But we further ſay, That laying on of hands is not figurative, but is a plain practical Ordinance, joyned with ſolemn and fervent Prayer to the moſt High, in the Name of Chriſt, for his holy Spirit, that according to his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and never-failing promiſe, them that believe and are baptiſed in the Name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, might receive the Spirit; by which, as the means, the Spirit was given to ſome of the Baptiſed in the <hi>primitive times,</hi> in more than an ordinary manner, and was neceſſary to the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing Chriſtian Churches; than which extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Gifts of the Spirit given then, is a confirmation to us now, that not onely the other Principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt are to be believed and practiſed, but this in debate alſo, as one Principle of the Foundation of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, God having confirmed them all to be the Word ſpoken, and Foundation-Doctrine taught by the Lord, bearing witneſs to them, both with Signs and Wonders, and divers Miracles, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:110647:47"/> Gifts of the holy Ghoſt, according to his own will; and then <hi>how ſhall we eſcape, if we neglect ſo great Salvation?</hi> Heb. 2.3, 4.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 27.</head>
               <p>If you ſhall ſay, That ſimply the Act and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony it ſelf as you practiſe it, is put for a Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Doctrine of Chriſt; then we demand, Whether the Apoſtles ever taught any thing for a Doctrine of Chriſt, whereof we do not read Chriſt did either preach or practiſe before his Aſcenſion? And if you ſay, That Chriſt did teach and practiſe laying on of hands upon all Diſciples, both Men and Women, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Aſcenſion, or any thing from which ſuch a practice may be inferred, pray ſhew it, and we will believe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We ſay, That Prayer and Laying on of hands, as we practiſe, is a Principle of the Doctrine of Chriſt, one of the firſt Rudiments of Chriſtianity.</p>
               <p>But you demand, Whether the Apoſtles ever taught any thing for a Doctrine of Chriſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we do not read Chriſt did either preach or practiſe before his Aſcenſion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What is it to the purpoſe when Chriſt taught laying on of hands, whether before his Paſſion, or after; or before his Aſcention, or after by his Spirit? It ſufficeth he did teach it, for it is one of the Principles of his Doctrine: And can it be a Principle of his Doctrine, and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:110647:48"/> he not teach it? We are certain it cannot: And taught it was likewiſe by his Apoſtles, for a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine-Principle, and an Oracle of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12. &amp; 6.1. and they did not only teach, but pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe it alſo, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.17. &amp; 19.6. And do you think they would both teach and practiſe it, and never receive it from Chriſt, but muſt invent it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs? We cannot believe you do ſo think: Then was it taught by Chriſt, and taught and practiſed by his Apoſtles, as a foundation-Principle. And that ſufficeth us, and might you, if you were willing and obedient. See this anſwered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in <hi>Chriſts Doctrine,</hi> p. 58.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 28.</head>
               <p>If laying on of hands upon all baptiſed Believers be to be practiſed in your ſence, as an indiſpenſable Duty; then we demand, Why all the other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples in <hi>Heb. 6.</hi> ſhould be expreſly and particularly commanded, believed, or practiſed in Chriſts time, and not this, as it is practiſed by you, if there be that weight in it, as you lay upon it? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. If laying on of hands (ſay you) upon all baptiſed Believers, be to be practiſed in our ſence, as an indiſpenſable Duty; then you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, Why all the other Principles, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. ſhould be expreſly commanded, believed, and practiſed in Chriſts time, and not this, as it is practiſed by us, if there be that weight in it as we lay upon it? We told you above, that it
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:110647:48"/> matters not when Chriſt taught laying on of hands, whether in the time of his Life, or not. And whereas you ſay, <hi>That Faith, and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, the Baptiſm of Water, the Reſurrection of the Dead, and eternal Judgement, were in Chriſts time plainly taught:</hi> Pray where did Chriſt in the time of his Life, before his Aſcenſion, or after it either, ſo plainly command baptiſing with water? Though we do not deny but there was both Faith, Repentance, the Reſurrection, and eternal Judgement, plainly enough taught, according to that Diſpenſation; and ſo they were before Chriſts Incarnation, by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of old; nor do we deny, but grant, that there was Authority enough from Heaven for the Baptiſm of Water then practiſed; and that there was them that did fore-tell that the holy Spirit ſhould be afterwards given, and ſo it was by the Prophet <hi>Joel;</hi> all which were as prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to what afterward Chriſt ſhould command and teach, when he had ſuffered and was riſen, and all power in Heaven and Earth was given unto him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18. So <hi>John</hi> was ſent to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the way, and he taught the Baptiſm of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, ſaying, They ſhould believe on him that was to come; ſo that between both the Faith and the Baptiſm then, and that after Chriſt was come, had ſuffered, aſcended, and the holy Ghoſt was given, there muſt needs be a vaſt difference; therefore (as you affirm) <hi>Paul</hi>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:110647:49"/> baptiſed the twelve Diſciples he found at <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> again, becauſe they were onely baptiſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm; who, as was his Baptiſm, ſo was his Doctrine of Faith and Repentance: <hi>John verily baptiſed with the Baptiſm of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, ſaying to the People, That they ſhould believe on him which ſhould come after him, that is, on Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Act. 19.4. From whence, or from which Diſpenſation, we do not take the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Foundation-Doctrine of Chriſt, no, not of Repentance, Faith, Baptiſms, Laying on of hands, Reſurrection, and eternal Judgement; but from Chriſt dead, riſen, and aſcended to the Father, from whom he ſent his holy Spirit to confirm them all to be his Doctrine, on which he hath built his Church: Yet might theſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples be (nay doubtleſs were) left and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Chriſt before his Aſcenſion, which they better underſtood and put in practice, when they were endowed with power from on high, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. by the Spirit of Truth, which Chriſt ſent to them, to guide them into all Truth, <hi>John</hi> 16.13. and of them whom Chriſt commanded by word of mouth to obſerve and teach theſe Principles, have we received them, as the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Lord Jeſus; of which Doctrine laying on of hands on baptiſed Believers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch, is one Principle, taught alſo by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and by them practiſed, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.17. &amp; 19.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> And if we do not find it was practiſed in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:110647:49"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ime of Chriſts life, that doth not make invalid what was taught and practiſed after his Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; He had many things to ſay in the time of his life, his Diſciples could not then bear, <hi>John</hi> 16.12. which he promiſeth to inſtruct them in by his Spirit, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13, 14, 15.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It being then clear, that laying on of hands is a Principle of the Doctrine of Chriſt; it's not to the thing in hand where, when, or how Chriſt taught it; but that you will ſtudy doubts rather than obedience. And whereas you ſpeak of the Doctrine of the holy Spirit, if the Truth were known, you as little believe it, as you practiſe laying on of hands for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of it, as will appear hereafter. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding from what hath been ſaid, That laying on of hands is as clear a Principle of Chriſts Doctrine, as any of the other are, having the ſame Authority; we refuſe, and keep no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Diſobedient.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 29.</head>
               <p>If you ſay, The practice of the Apoſtles, <hi>Act. 8.17.</hi> plainly ſhews that they had a Command for what they did; We thereupon demand, Though we read they baptiſed Men and Women promiſcouſly, yet where do you read they ever laid hands promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly upon Men and Women? If you ſhall ſay, It is implied in the word THEM, which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles laid their hands upon, which were the ſame THEM that <hi>Philip</hi> baptiſed; we demand, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:110647:50"/> it may not be as truly ſaid that <hi>Philip</hi> preache<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to every Man and Woman in <hi>Samaria,</hi> becauſe it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſaid, <hi>He went to the City of Samaria, and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Chriſt to them?</hi> verſ. <hi>5.</hi> And whether i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may not be as well ſaid, That every Man and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in <hi>Samaria</hi> believed and were baptiſed, becauſe it is ſaid, That <hi>Samaria had received the Word of God, and was baptized;</hi> as you may ſay, That becauſe the Church of Jeruſalem ſent unto <hi>Them Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> to lay hands on <hi>Them,</hi> that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt be underſtood they laid hands on every baptiſed Man and Woman? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We do ſay the practice of the Apoſtles, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.17. and elſewhere, doth plainly ſhew that they had received a Command from Chriſt for what they did; and ſo muſt you ſay, unleſs you will ſay it was their own humane invention. And if you think it was practiſed by them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out command from Chriſt, and ſo their own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, why do you not ſay ſo? But if you think they had received ſufficient Authority from Chriſt for what they did, why do you make oppoſition againſt their practice, and refuſe to follow them, as they followed Chriſt, and keep thoſe traditions they delivered.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But you demand, <hi>Though we read that they baptiſed both Men and Women promiſcuouſly, yet where do we read they ever laid hands promiſcuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon Men and Women?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:110647:50"/>
               <p>We ſay it is in ſo many words ſaid, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.12. they were baptiſed, both Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; and no leſs plain it is, that <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> prayed and laid their hands upon them, both Men and Women. For by as good reaſon may one conclude that <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were ſent by the reſt of the Apoſtles but to ſome of them that believed and were baptiſed at <hi>Samaria,</hi> as to conclude that <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> prayed for, and laid hands on, but ſome of them. Nor can it be as well ſaid that <hi>Philip</hi> preached to every Man and Woman in <hi>Samaria,</hi> becauſe it is ſaid that <hi>Philip</hi> went down to the City of <hi>Samaria,</hi> and preached Chriſt unto them; nor every Man and Woman in <hi>Samaria</hi> believed and Were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed, though it be ſaid <hi>Samaria</hi> had received the Word: the former being true, though he had preach'd but to twenty; and the latter, though but ſix believed and were baptiſed. And to conclude all in <hi>Samaria</hi> were preached to, believed, and were baptiſed, were not logical indeed; but to conclude that <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> prayed for, and laid hands on the Women that <hi>Philip</hi> baptiſed, as well as they prayed for, and laid their hands on the Men he baptiſed, is Scriptural and Logical; becauſe the Women had equal right to the Gift of the Spirit (which was the end of that ſervice) by vertue of Gods Promiſe to them, as well as to men, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28, 29. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.17, 18. Then is it Scriptural
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:110647:51"/> and Logical, to conclude that the baptiſed Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men had equal right to the means by which the Spirit was given, as well as the baptiſed Men.</p>
               <p n="3">3. So that the Truth is, (whereas you ſay, <hi>That we are ſo far from having a Command for lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands on all baptiſed Believers, that we have not a plain Example for it)</hi> you are ſo far from knowing and believing the Truth, that you will not ſee any Command there is, nor Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample neither, for laying on of hands on bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed Believers, as ſuch, that you ſtill remain contradicting, and putting it from you; thereby judging your ſelves unworthy of the bleſſing of Gods holy and guiding Spirit, which to his praiſe is receiv'd thereby: There being both Command and plain Example from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; which Command they received from Chriſt, and Chriſt from God his Father. See this anſwered before, in <hi>Gods Oracle,</hi> page 47, 48, 49.</p>
               <p n="4">4. But you ſay, <hi>Dr. Hamond queſtioneth which laying on of hands is here intended, and ſaith it is probable it was upon Diſciples, for the Gift of the Spirit; and doth confeſs there is a difficulty to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve whether it be for the laying on of hands for Confirmation or Ordination.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Hamond</hi> and you might conclude that it was not for Ordination, had you but conſulted <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> when he ſaith, <hi>A Novice muſt
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:110647:51"/> not be choſen or ordained a Biſhop, leſt being lifted up with pride, he fall into the condemnation of the Devil,</hi> 1 Tim. 3.6. Then could not <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> lay hands on the Baptiſed at <hi>Samaria</hi> for Ordination, becauſe they were but of yeſterday, newly come to the Faith. Moreover the very end of their laying on of hands was, <hi>That they might receive the holy Ghost,</hi> Act. 8.15. Now had your learned and judicious Doctor conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered theſe things, he would not have ſaid it was difficult to reſolve whether the laying on of hands, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.17. was for Confirmation or Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination.</p>
               <p n="5">5. But we perceive the Authority of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor goes very far with you, that you will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve when he believes, and doubt of what he doubts: That if he had ſaid there is a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for laying on of hands, and a plain Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, peradventure you would ſay ſo too. For you ſay, <hi>And therefore though laying on of hands as we practiſe it, be true; yet it is not ſo infallibly true, becauſe it depends upon our Expoſition.</hi> If you had drawn your concluſion right, from what was before premiſed by you, it muſt have been thus: <hi>Therefore though laying on of hands as we practiſe it, be true; yet it is not infallibly true, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Dr.</hi> Hamond <hi>is at a ſtand about it and ſaith it is difficult to reſolve whether it be for Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Ordination:</hi> and not ſay, <hi>Becauſe it depends upon our Expoſition,</hi> which it doth not; for we have
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:110647:52"/> plain words and practice for it, in the Scripture, there being from this Text, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.17. plain and clear Example for laying on of hands both on Men and Woman, and not conjectural and gueſs'd at; we have good reaſon to divide from you about it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 30</head>
               <p>Suppoſe we had a plain Example that they laid hands on Men and Women promiſcuouſly, this being but an Example, and no Command preceding it; how could it become binding, ſo as to give you a ground to ſeparate about it?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>We have plain example without ſuppoſition, that the Apoſtles laid on hands both on Men Women; yet you ſay, <hi>This being but an Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and no Command preceding it, how could it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come binding, ſo as to give us ground to ſeparate about it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How uncharitable (to ſay no worſe) do you here ſecretly charge the Apoſtles with practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that for which they had received no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from Chriſt to practiſe? What unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs were it for them to ſet up their poſt by their Lord and Maſters? And if they were ſo unfaithful in one thing, how can we give them ſo much credit as to believe and follow them in any thing? But we firmly believe, and make no doubt (though you beg the queſtion, by conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they had no Command to warrant what
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:110647:52"/> they did) but they had a Command from Chriſt for what they did, when they laid hands on the baptiſed Believers in <hi>Samaria,</hi> or they had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver put it in practiſe, and left it upon Record for future Ages to read, as we could abundantly prove, againſt all ſuch Quarrels you or any other ſhall pick with them. You ſtill give more ground to ſeparate about it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 31.</head>
               <p>But if you ſhall ſay the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> did lay hands upon the Diſciples of <hi>Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſus, Act. 19.</hi> and therefore it was ſurely commanded; we demand whether <hi>Paul</hi> did not alſo baptiſe the ſame perſons after they had been baptized into <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm, as appears he did, <hi>verſ. 5.</hi> and why ſhould not his baptizing them again be a Fundamental Doctrine, ſince the Doctrine of BAPTISMS is as much a Fundamental Doctrine, as laying on of hands? <hi>Heb. 6.2.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And why may you not as well produce the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Example, <hi>Act. 19.</hi> for the Explication of the Doctrine of Baptiſms, <hi>Heb. 6.</hi> ſeeing he baptiſed thoſe that had been baptiſed before, and ſo baptiſe all our Members again, that come to you; as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce this Example for the explaining the Doctrine of laying on of hands?</p>
               <p>We demand then what can be inferred from hence to prove it an unqueſtionable Duty? And if not, why ſhould you divide about it?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:110647:53"/>
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We do ſay the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> did lay on hands upon the Diſciples at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> Act. 19. and therefore it was ſurely commanded him, and ſo us, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.17. &amp; 4.8, 9. that have belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved on Chriſt through their word, <hi>John</hi> 17.20. You then demand whether <hi>Paul</hi> did not alſo baptiſe the ſame perſons, after they had been baptiſed into <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm? And then you anſwer your ſelves, and ſay, It appears he did, verſ. 5.</p>
               <p>And then you ask, <hi>Why ſhould not his baptizing them again be a Fundamental Doctrine, ſince the Doctrine of Baptiſms is as much a Fundamental Doctrine as laying on of hands?</hi> Heb. 6.2.</p>
               <p>We do not ſay but his baptiſing them again was a Fundamental Doctrine.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But then you enquire, <hi>Why we may not as well produce the Apoſtles example,</hi> Acts 19. <hi>for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the Doctrine of Baptiſms,</hi> Heb. 6. <hi>ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he baptiſed thoſe that had been baptiſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When we meet with the ſame caſe, we ſhall have occaſion to make uſe of that ex<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mple to explain the Doctrine of Baptiſms, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. till then, we need not.</p>
               <p>Then you further ſay, <hi>And ſo baptiſe all your Members again that come to us, as produce this Example for the explaining the Doctrine of laying on of hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:110647:53"/>
               <p>Had your Members known no more than the Baptiſm of <hi>John,</hi> and had been baptiſed into <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſm; we ſhould have baptiſed them all again; but as they profeſt, and we believed, they were baptiſed in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, we had no reaſon to baptiſe them again, and ſo no occaſion to produce that Example, to explicate the Doctrine of Baptiſms, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. as we have of laying on of hands.</p>
               <p>And from this Example of <hi>Paul</hi>'s laying on of hands on the twelve Diſciples he found at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> Act. 19. we infer that he, as well as <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> Act. 8. had Chriſts Doctrine for his practice; and that therefore it is an unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable Duty. We have then good reaſon to divide from you about it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 32.</head>
               <p>We demand where-ever you read of the practice of laying on of hands by Christians, before the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Gifts of the Spirit were given, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for the Work of the Miniſtry? If you ſay it was practiſed before, then we deſire that you would ſhew us where it was practiſed?</p>
               <p>And if it was not practiſed it was either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was not commanded before, or elſe it muſt needs be that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey were all negligent of their Duty, which is uncharitable to conceive; or elſe it muſt needs be that though Christ did command it, yet they were to ſuſpend their practiſe of it till they had received the extraordinary Gifts of the Spirit. If
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:110647:54"/> you ſay it was commanded before Chriſt did aſcend, but the practice was ſuſpended during the abſence of the extraordinary Gifts of the Spirit, becauſe there was no reaſon why the Apoſtles ſhould lay hands on others, in order to the reception of the extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Gifts of the Spirit, when they had not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived thoſe Gifts themſelves.</p>
               <p>Then we further demand, If that laying on of hands could be proved a Command in the ſenſe you contend for, whether we may not be excuſed from either doing or receiving of it NOW, while the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Gifts are abſent, both from him that administers it, and they that receive it?</p>
               <p>But if you ſhall ſay, This Objection lieth againſt Baptiſm, as well as laying on of hands; then we demand how that can be? Since Baptiſm was practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed before the extraordinary Gifts were given, ſo was not this laying on of hands: Baptiſm was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred by them that never did Miracles, ſo was not laying on of hands: Again, Baptiſm was practiſed on them that had received the Gifts of the holy Ghoſt before they were baptiſed; but where do you read of any that having firſt received the holy Ghoſt before laying on of hands, that afterwards had laying on of hands adminiſtred unto them? So that till this doubt be removed, what ground have you to divide about it?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. What if we grant that laying on of hands was not practiſed before the Spirit was given,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:110647:54"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y which they were endowed with power from on high, to put in practiſe laying on of hands, and all other practical Duties? And what if we ſay that laying on of hands, and alſo other Duties that were commanded by Chriſt after his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſſion, and before his Aſcenſion, were all ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended till the Apoſtles were endowed with power from on high, and during the abſence of the Spirit; yet not for the reaſon you give, but for reaſons we have and ſhall give, when they ſhall meet with due place.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That there is a Command for laying on of hands, is ſufficiently proved, and therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our not receiving it Now, though the extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Gifts of the Spirit be abſent, will not be excuſed. Let us unfold this Myſtery: For you hereby ſecretly conclude, that they that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred laying on of hands then, had the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Gifts of the Spirit; but no man hath the extraordinary Gifts of the Spirit now; therefore we may be excuſed from receiving laying on of hands now. We ſay if this be good reaſon, it will lay aſide, as not practical, the whole Doctrine of Chriſt, thus: They that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reached Repentance and Faith, the Doctrine of Baptiſms, and Laying on of Hands, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Dead, and eternal Judgement, then, had received the extraordinary Gifts of the Spirit: No man hath the extraordinary Gifts of the Spirit now? Therefore all men
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:110647:55"/> may be excuſed from preaching and from he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing the Doctrine of Repentance, Faith, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Doctrine of Baptiſms, of Laying on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hands, the Reſurrection of the Dead, et<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nal Judgement, now. And what is the tende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy of ſuch reaſoning, but Infidelity and Ath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iſm? And whereas you think to be excuſed fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> laying on of hands, becauſe the extraordinar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gifts of the Spirit are not given now; we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that will not excuſe you before Chriſt at his ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pearing, becauſe you crave excuſe upon a fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> bottom; ſuppoſing that the extraordinary Gif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Spirit was the onely end of the practi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the laying on of hands; yet was it not, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the reception of the Spirit only was as a com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon end aſſigned, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.15. of prayer and la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing on of hands, and not this or that Gift there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of, ordinary or extraordinary: Though it's true the extraordinary Gifts of the Spirit were give<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon prayer &amp; laying on of hands; God appear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing ſo eminently in that Appointment, did be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> witneſs &amp; confirm it to be part of that word ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken by the Lord, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.4. yet was thoſe Gifts ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver propounded as the end of laying on of hands no more than they were promiſed to them tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obeyed Chriſt by repenting, and being baptiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in his name, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38, 39. &amp; 5.32. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> though the extraordinary Gifts of the Spirit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not now given, that will not excuſe your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to Chriſt, in not doing or receivin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:110647:55"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> now. And truly the reaſon (if we may ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all it) that you make your Plea, doth lie againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aptiſm, and all other Goſpel-Duties, as we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ewed before.</p>
               <p>But then you demand, <hi>How that can be, ſince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aptiſm was practiſed before the extraordinary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ifts were given?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We ſay the Baptiſm of <hi>John</hi> was practiſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or the extraordinary Gifts were given.</p>
               <p>But then you ſay, <hi>Baptiſm was adminiſtred by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>em that never did miracles, ſo was not Laying on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f Hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We grant you <hi>John</hi> baptiſed and did no mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e; but how do you know laying on of hands <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as not adminiſtred by them that never did mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cles? What miracle did <hi>Ananias</hi> do? <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>Again, you ſay, <hi>Baptiſm was practiſed on them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> had received the Gifts of the holy Ghoſt before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ey were baptiſed; but where do we read of any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>at having firſt received the holy Ghoſt before lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng on of hands, that afterward had laying on of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ands adminiſtred to them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We ſay that neither we nor you read that any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d received the Spirit before laying on of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ands was firſt adminiſtred to them, ſaving <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elius</hi> and his houſhold, <hi>Act.</hi> 10. who indeed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eceived the Gifts of the holy Ghoſt before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aptiſm, or laying on of hands either; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat then? What if the like inſtance is not to
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:110647:56"/> be read, the Scripture being ſilent in the Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> whether <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his Houſhold had layin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on of hands adminiſtred to them? VVill th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> leſſen the Authority of any part of the Do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt, and make void and null <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Apoſtolical and Primitive Practice?</p>
               <p>Further, Though what you demand is not to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> read, yet let us tell you that what you ſay wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> lie as full in the reaſon of it againſt Baptiſm, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> you conceit it doth againſt laying on of hands becauſe the Gift of the Spirit in the promiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it, is annexed to Baptiſm, as the Gift of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Spirit was aſſigned in laying on of hands, as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> end of it: Now <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his Houſhold ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no reaſon to be baptiſed in Water, becauſe the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> had firſt received and poſſeſſed that, which wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> baptiſed they could not lay claim to any thing more than the promiſe of; no reaſon, we ſay, but the Authority of the Lord Jeſus, who ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> commanded it: And therefore though they had received the Spirit before they were baptiſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet muſt they be baptiſed in Water, in obedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence to Chriſts Doctrine and Command. So i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> like manner, if <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his Houſhold mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> be baptiſed, though he had firſt received the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which Gad had annexed the promiſe of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Baptiſm; then muſt they be bound in Duty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> well to ſubmit to laying on of hands, thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Spirit be aſſigned as the end thereof, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they had firſt received the Gift of the Spiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:110647:56"/> before laying on of hands, from the ſame reaſon of obedience to Chriſts Doctrine and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, though we do not read it was admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred unto them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. But what is this to your Caſe? Do any of you pretend to have ſuch a meaſure of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit as <hi>Cornelius</hi> had; or ſo much, you need not that any ſhould adminiſter laying on of hands, that you might have more, and ſo think to be excuſed doing or receiving it? O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> do you doubt whether it be your Duty to practiſe it, becauſe the extraordinary Gifts of the Spirit are now abſent? Your Doubts now being removed, we have the ſame ground left we ever had, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide from you about it, till you ſhall remove our ground by doing and receiving it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 33.</head>
               <p>Whether it be not uncharitable for you to ſay we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ppoſe or deny laying on of hands, becauſe for the reaſons implied in the former Queſtions, we queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your practiſe of it, with reſpect to its being a Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty incumbent upon all Diſciples? May you not as well ſay, That thoſe people that believe not that Chriſt died for all, do deny the Death of Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do not believe he hath died for all; as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> may ſay we deny laying on of hands a Duty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we do not believe it a Duty for every Man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd Woman that is baptiſed? And may you not as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll ſay, They denied the Prieſtly Office of Chriſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>5.</hi> that were ignorant of many things that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:110647:57"/> thereunto, as ſay that we oppoſe a Doctrine of Chriſt, becauſe we are ignorant of ſomething rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to it, which for the reaſons implied in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer queſtion, we cannot yet underſtand? And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, may we not as truly ſay, Many of you deny Christ, and ſo have not God, becauſe they deny he took Fleſh of the Virgin Mary, as ſay we deny a Doctrine of Christ, becauſe we deny, or rather doubt, of laying on of hands on all Diſciples, Men and Women, as you practiſe it?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. To ſay the Truth, is not to be uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and when we ſay you oppoſe or deny lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands, as you have done more than twenty years, is not to be (we hope) uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: For that laying on of hands we practiſe, you do deny and oppoſe, though you may co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour your oppoſition under the pretence of doubts and queſtions, and under the pretence of owning laying on of hands to heal the Sick, or to ſet Men apart to Office in the Church, though not on all baptiſed Men and Women, that they might receive the Spirit: Nor is your reaſon by which you would wipe off that blemiſh ſufficient, for we may not as well ſay that thoſe people which believe not that Chriſt died for all, do deny the Death of Chriſt; becauſe the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> do believe he died, and died for them, and more too: But you do not believe that layin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on of hands on baptiſed Believers as ſuch, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:110647:57"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ey might receive the Spirit, is the duty of any.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Neither can it be ſaid, that the Hebrew Church denied the Prieſtly Office of Chriſt, becauſe they were dull of hearing, and could not receive thoſe great Myſteries thereof that were hard to be uttered, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.11. And though you pretend you are ignorant, yet we think you would not take it well ſhould we ſet you down for ſuch. And as for what you may ſay, ſay your pleaſure; and ſay if you will, many of us (if you ſay true) deny Chriſt took fleſh of the Virgin <hi>Mary:</hi> We can ſay, and ſay truth, that many of you deny Chriſt, and have not God, becauſe you deny him to be God of one Subſtance with the Father; and ſay that he is a created being, and took his begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the Womb of the Virgin, beſides your denying laying on of Hands on all Diſciples, Men and Women, as we practiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 34.</head>
               <p>Did you ever come to us, or ſend any to us, to lay Hands upon us, and we rejected you? why then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ould you reject us?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>When we firſt received laying on of Hands, we were with you, and continued reaſoning, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d perſwading you to receive the truth; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> then oppoſed us, and it; yea, and at length <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e hardned and believed not, but ſpake evil
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:110647:58"/> of the way, and then we departed and ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from you; and know no reaſon we have to come, or ſend to you to lay Hands on you, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you repent, and receive the truth candid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the love of it, until then we have reaſon to reject you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 35.</head>
               <p>Do we not practiſe laying on of hands upon Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, and are not many willing to ſubmit to it a Members for peace and accommodation ſake, and together with you wait upon God for further light in this matter? why then ſhould you impoſe believing of it on us as a Command upon all Diſciples both Men and Women: I, and ſuch a Command as is eſſential to Communion and Church-memberſhip, when you have no ſuch Command nor Example in all the Scriptures, either that it was practiſed upon Men and Women that were Baptized, or that it was judged eſſential to Communion, or that it was ever practiſed, but on the account of the extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary gifts of the Spirit, or that it was ever ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred on any, if they had received the gifts of the Spirit before?</p>
               <p>Till theſe ſober Scruples are removed, and the Duty of Laying on of Hands proved eſſential to Communion, what ground have you to refuſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with us?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>We know not whether you practiſe laying on of Hands upon Officers or no; but if you
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:110647:58"/> do, what Command have you for it? Nor are thoſe terms for peace and accommodation ſake ſufficient, Chriſt hath no need to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to you; Where do you read that any were received to, or practiſed any Goſpel Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance upon thoſe terms? We muſt therefore, if you receive it from us, impoſe it upon you as a Command upon all Diſciples both Men and Women, becauſe it is ſo, as appears <hi>Acts</hi> 8. for the Apoſtles practiſed no more, in Holy and Divine Adoration and Invocation, than what they were taught and commanded by their Lord and Maſter Chriſt to do; yea, and ſuch a Command (or rather Duty) it is, that is eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to Communion, and Church-memberſhip, we having both Command and Example in the Scripture, as we have ſhewed; and it would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e but reiteration to ſhew it here again, nor was it practiſed upon the account of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary gifts of the Spirit, the Scripture no where aſſigning them as the end there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And if the Scripture be ſilent in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſe of Laying on of Hands on <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his Houſe, it doth not follow but that he did receive laying on of Hands after he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Spirit, as well as his being Baptiſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Water after he had received the Spirit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here being the ſame weighty and preſſing rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons for both, <hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt's Doctrine and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:110647:59"/> We do not know when you will ſay your ſober Scruples are removed: for Laying on of Hands is proved to be eſſential to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; therefore we have ground to refuſe Communion with you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 36.</head>
               <p>Are you not divided among your ſelves in this matter? have not ſome of you ſaid Laying on of Hands was for Confirmation? Others, that it was for the extraordinary gifts of the Spirit? Others, that it was for the Spirit in any meaſure?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>We know not any that ſaith, That Laying on of Hands was for the extraordinary gifts of the Spirit, but you and others of your mind; and if ſome do ſay that Laying on of Hands is for the receiving the Spirit in any meaſure; and others will ſay it was for Confirmation; there is not much difference between them: we ſay then, we are not divided among our ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout laying on of Hands.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 37.</head>
               <p>Have not others of you both Printed and Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, that Laying on of Hands is one of the ſever Pillars that Wiſdom builded her houſe upon, <hi>Prov. 9.1.</hi> and may not the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> as wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> prove her ſeven Sacraments from hence, as you prove Laying on of Hands? Beſides, do you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by thus expounding the Word of God create ſever Principles inſtead of ſix you talk of? and may y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:110647:59"/> not as well ſay that becauſe the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> Wall had twelve Foundations, that therefore the Church muſt have twelve Fundamentals, without which ſhe cannot be a Church communicable?</p>
               <p>Is not this making the Word of God like the <hi>Lesbian</hi> Rule, who having built crooked and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular, ſo as the Work was not conformable to the Rule, went and made their Rule conformable to their Work?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. What if ſome of us have from thoſe Pillars Wiſdom builded her houſe upon, <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.1. alluded to the Foundation Doctrine of Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2. and of the Apoſtles, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.20. But if you ſhall ſay that <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2. makes mention but of ſix Principles, and <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.1. mentions ſeven Pillars; we hope you that ſay Chriſt is the Foundation, and thoſe Principles cannot be a Foundation, nor no part of the Foundation of Chriſtianity, will not be againſt it, if ſome of us do ſay, that Chriſt being the Chief Corner-ſtone in that Foundation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. and ſo that text, <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.1. may allude to ſeven.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And pray, is there not as good a harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and analogy between <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.1. &amp; <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. and <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.20. as you can have ground of proof from <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.19, 22, 23. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 34.9. That the Apoſtles, in divers caſes, laid on Hands, not in conformity to a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:110647:60"/> but by way of accommodation to the laudable Cuſtoms of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> as in your 23d <hi>Queſtion</hi> you do.</p>
               <p n="3">3. You go about to prove from thoſe places, and conclude the Apoſtles did ſo; but who do you know either by Printing or Preaching, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to prove that laying on of hands is Commanded, or is a Duty, to be practiſed from <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.1. as you do to prove the other from thoſe places mentioned above; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing might be offered from thence as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and by way of illuſtration. Then is your talk but idle about <hi>Romes</hi> ſeven Sacraments, and the twelve Foundations of <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> Wall, and your <hi>Lesbian</hi> Rule; for who would make the Rule conform to the Work more than you, which have built your houſe irregularly, and crooked, and, ſo would if you could tell how, have the Word, which is the Rule, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to your Work.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 38.</head>
               <p>And whereas the Scripture tells us of ſeveral laying on of hands, and we have oftentimes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded how you prove that the laying on of hands, as practiſed by you, is that ſpoke of in <hi>Heb. 6.</hi> you anſwer, if we would have a proof in ſo many words, that ſaith ſuch a laying on of hands, as you practiſe is there mentioned, we muſt ſeek one our ſelves, for you have none; then we demand, whether you ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not very uncharitable to exclude any from the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:110647:60"/> Communion of Gods Church, becauſe they cannot ſee that to be a Duty, which you have no plain Text for the proof of, by your own Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. As often as you have demanded, how we prove that the laying on of hands we practiſe, is that meant <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. ſo often you have been anſwered; but you may well bluſh for ſhame, that ſo falſly render what we have ſaid in this matter. Do we ſay, as you conclude, that we have no plain Text to prove laying on of hands to be a Duty? where or when did any of us ever ſay ſo? You quote indeed <hi>Gods Oracle and Chriſts Doctrine,</hi> page 52. but 'tis page the 53. and there let the moſt prejudiced Reader uſe but reaſon, ſee and judge whether you are not moſt injurious to the truth and us; and let any impartial Reader weigh well what is ſaid before, in that Book, and they will find we have ſufficiently proved, that the laying on of Hands on baptiſed Believers, as ſuch, is that laying on of hands, mentioned <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. there ſaid to be a Foundation-Principle.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is true, there is no Text that doth ſay in ſo many words, that that laying on of hands <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. is the laying on of hands to heal the ſick, nor that to ſet men apart to Office in the Church, nor that it is Laying on of Hands on baptiſed Believers; What then? Chriſt ſaith,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:110647:61"/> 
                  <hi>Go teach all Nations, baptizing them,</hi> Matth. 28.19. And the Scripture mentions ſeveral Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſms; and there be ſome that deny Baptiſm of Water; where have you a Text that in ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny words will ſay, That the Baptiſm of Water which you practiſe, is the Baptiſm-Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. You muſt confeſs you have none; and can it be fairly &amp; honeſtly concluded that therefore you have no plain Text for the proof of your practice, as you do by us; let the Reader conſult <hi>Gods Oracle and Chriſts Doctrine</hi> from page 44. to page 54. where it is ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved, That the laying on of hands men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. is the laying on of hands on baptiſed Believers, practiſed by the Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.17. and 19.6. Then are we not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable, though we exclude you from the Communion of Gods Church, becauſe you do not do your Duty, which we have plain Texts, and ſound Reaſon for the proof of.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 39.</head>
               <p>And whereas you ſay the Apoſtles practice must expound the <hi>6th</hi> of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> in this caſe as well as in Water-Baptiſm; we anſwer ſo it ſhall. But then where did they lay hands on Women, and where did they Command laying on of hands in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, as they did in Baptiſm, <hi>Acts 12.8. Acts 10.47.48.</hi> and where did they lay hands ON any, after they had received the gifts of the Spirit? but we do find they Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:110647:61"/> them afterwards, I, and Commanded ſuch to ſubmit to it in the Name of the Lord Jeſus: produce us the like Inſtances, and you ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>If the Apoſtles practice ſhall expound <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. as well as in the caſe of Baptiſm, Then have you never a Text in all the Scripture that will in ſo many words ſay, Chriſt meant Water-bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, when he ſaith, <hi>Go teach all Nations, bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing them,</hi> but muſt expound the Commiſſion by their practice, and then how unworthily have you done by the Truth, concluding as you do in the 38. <hi>Queſtion:</hi> But then, inſtead of doing what you ſay the Apoſtles practice ſhal expound, you leave the matter, and ask where they laid hands on Women: Why we told you that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp; you may read <hi>Acts</hi> 8. and then you ask, where they Commanded laying on of hands in the Name of Chriſt? We will leave that to you to determine in whoſe Name the Apoſtles did it and commanded it; &amp; then you ask, where did they lay on hands on any after they received the gifts of the Spirit? though we have anſwered this twice before, but you never ſpoke one word to that Caſe you ſo falſly render; and then as falſly conclude, that we confeſs we have no plain Text for the proof of laying on of hands, but bid us produce the like Inſtances, and we ſay ſomething. Suppoſe there be not
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:110647:62"/> the like Inſtances to be produced in all occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Circumſtances, or otherwiſe in Baptiſm o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Water, as is in thoſe Principles of Faith a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Repentance; will all that can be ſaid for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Baptiſm of Water be nothing, except the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> can be produced is many Inſtances agreeing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all reſpects to Baptiſm as agrees in expreſſne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of terms to Repentance and Faith? if ſo, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> if Baptiſm of Water be no Duty except as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> foreſaid; you will not be able, nor none elſe to give ſuch proof for water Baptiſm, nor ſome other practice you will own to enforce the du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of it on any that ſhall oppoſe you. VV<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> having ſaid then ſo much for laying on of hand as you will never be able to un-ſay from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or Reaſon; nor can anſwer, except it b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by granting it to be by Scripture proved a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation-Principle of Chriſts Doctrine, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly ſubmit to it upon Chriſts terms, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then you will not onely ſay, but do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="question">
               <head>Queſt. 40.</head>
               <p>Again, whereas you have both Preached <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Printed that you cannot prove laying on of hand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as you practiſe it, any otherwiſe than by Inferen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Deductions; how can you be ſo daringly con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fident as to call thoſe things Gods Oracles and Eſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſentials of Religion, that are but your interpre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions of Scripture, unleſs with the Church of Rome you will ſay the Church cannot err?</p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:110647:62"/>
               <p>Not but that we believe many profitable truths may be collected and infer'd by conſequence from Scripture, <hi>And Conjectures (as one well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves) if mannerly obſerving their diſtance; and not impudently obtruding themſelves, for certainties, deſerve (if not to be received) to be conſidered.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that if Laying on of Hands in your ſenſe ſhould be a truth, yet it being but conjecturally ſo; We Query, why it ſhould be advanced into the number of thoſe expreſs Duties which are eſſential to Salvation and Church Communion?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>How can you be ſo daringly impudent as to forge ſuch an untruth, and ſay that we have both Preached, and Printed, that we cannot prove laying on of hands as we practiſe it, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then by Inferences and Deductions? where is ſuch a thing Printed, or who ever Preached ſo, that hath not turned back to his vomit, in ſome degree, or hath not out-lived his love to thoſe Principles he had received, and was once built on? May you not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of this, when we have again and again, by Printing, Preaching, and otherwiſe, proved laying on of hands, as practiſe it, to be a Foundation-Principle of Chriſts Doctrine, by plain and uninterpreted Scripture, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Inferences and Deductions, as fully as any Duty that is practical, can be proved without
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:110647:63"/> them, and was never refuted by you yet; how then can you ſtand in the face of God and his Congregation when you dare do thus! Had there been upon you the feeling thoughts of thoſe Texts, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8. &amp; 22.15. you would not have brought forth ſuch a Monſter into the world; it being therefore falſe what you ſay, we dare be ſo confident as to call laying on of hands as we practiſe it, one of the firſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Oracles of God, and an eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of Religion (without ſaying with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Church cannot err) (we will leave that for you to ſay) and with as much manners and modeſty as the authority of ſo ſacred an Ordinance will permit.</p>
               <p>Laying on of Hands then is a Truth, and ſuch a one as is by Chriſt and his Apoſtles (not by us) advanced (as you call it) into the number of thoſe expreſs Duties which are Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential to Church-Conſtitution and Church-Communion.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POST-SCRIPT.</head>
            <p>SInce the <hi>Searchers for Schiſm</hi> did direct their <hi>Queſtions</hi> to the <hi>Baptized Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> under <hi>Laying on of Hands,</hi> and did expect an <hi>Anſwer</hi> from them, as appears by the latter
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:110647:63"/> end of their <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> it may by ſome be thought ſtrange that I ſhould undertake to <hi>Anſwer</hi> them, ſeing they were propounded to the above-ſaid <hi>Congregations</hi> in general: That therefore which hath moved me thereunto, was partly the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of ſome Friends, it being ſome conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable time after I ſaw their <hi>Queſtions</hi> ere I had any thoughts to offer any thing in <hi>Anſwer</hi> to them (at leaſt in ſo publick a manner) thinking it was more the Concern of ſome other of my Brethren to engage now than mine, becauſe I had once and again appeared in Print (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my ability) in anſwer to thoſe gainſayers and oppoſers of <hi>laying on of hands;</hi> but they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſilent, whoſe Zeal for Truth ſhould (as I might well hope and expect) have put them with much forwardneſs upon the <hi>work,</hi> together with the <hi>report</hi> that went abroad how many young and weak Chriſtians were ſomewhat moved and ſtumbled, &amp; others that have declined (in ſome ſort) the Truth, did boaſt and were encouraged, put me upon this <hi>third Encounter,</hi> being not well able to forbear, having to this day (praiſed be the Lord my God) remaining in me ſome love to Chriſt, and to that ſacred and precious Word of his, <hi>viz. Laying on of Hands,</hi> yea, and to the ſouls of them who are ready to be toſſed to and fro with every wind of Doctrine, and among the reſt by the blaſt which was blown from the Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows of thoſe <hi>Queſtions,</hi> which their Authors
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:110647:64"/> pretend are for <hi>Conſcience ſake;</hi> but however, whether they were for Conſcience-ſake, or for Strife and Contention, this I can truly ſay, they are anſwered with good conſcience to God and love to the Authors of them, that God may be glorified by their obedience, and by the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing and confirmation of the Churches in the Doctrine of the Lord Jeſus; from part of which (at leaſt) it both hath been, and ſtill is (the more it is to be lamented) the endeavour of ſome, eſpecially the Authors of theſe <hi>Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> (who not only now, but heretofore have la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured) to trouble the peace of them which have obeyed that form of Doctrine which Chriſt taught, and was delivered by his Apoſtles to the primitive Saints.</p>
            <p>But let my ends and aims in what I have writ be what I ſay they are, yea, and had I the Pen of never ſo ready and exquiſit a Writer, yet muſt I not expect, nor do, but to be ſmitten for my love and pains, by them who bend their tongue like their bow for lyes, but are not valiant for the Truth upon the Earth, it being too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſeen that <hi>he which departs from iniquity makes himſelf a prey,</hi> when <hi>he that runs with a multitude to do evil ſhall have honour and praiſe;</hi> but however I am eſteemed, my comfort is I ſeek not the honour nor praiſe of men, neither do I fear the ſlanderous tongues of any, mine only end (as God knoweth) being their ſoul<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:110647:64"/> eternal felicity, who ſhall carp at me, be it the Inquirers or others; and therefore ſhould they reward me with evil for the good I intend them, they will in ſo doing wrong themſelves and not me. I will then leave the iſſue of theſe <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wers</hi> of their <hi>Queſtions</hi> to the Lord, heartily deſiring that Truth and Righteouſneſs were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced in ſincere love, by all them that name the Name of Chriſt, that there may be a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting from Iniquity and Error, which is the cauſe of all Diviſions, and then, and not till then will the Wound be healed. Had the <hi>Search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for Schiſm</hi> then conſidered that their Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to, and Errour in a Fundamental-Principle, is the cauſe why thoſe under <hi>Laying on of hands</hi> can have no Communion with them (which I hope this brief <hi>Anſwer</hi> to their <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions</hi> may help them to ſee) they would not be ſo irrational to conclude that Schiſm ſhould be found where Truth is obeyed and walked in; but that it is more likely by far to be where Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and Diſobedience dwells, and ſuch to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Dividers who refuſe to obey, but no more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow: only deſiring the Lord to make my poor Endeavours a Bleſſing to the Souls of them, and all others, and then I have my End.</p>
            <trailer>VALE.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
